it often has felt like to me as I've
learned more and more like oh my God
wait a minute we've just kind of treated
women and our health almost like if
you're golfing there's the tea That's
further back for the guys and there's
the tea that's a little bit like closer
for the women and we're just going to
treat everybody the same but shrink it a
little bit we'll take running shoes or a
bicycle all they do is they make it a
little bit smaller maybe put some pink
on it and say it's a woman's product we
experience things differently as women
than men do but that's not ever really
explained when we look at the trends of
the fasted training don't eat be it's
all on maale data if you look at most
women who make a point to get up do some
training go
exercise and after four weeks of
following the same kind of training
program as their male partner their male
partner has gotten leaner fitter better
focus all of the things that you want at
of fitness and the woman's like how come
I'm fatter and tired we have gotten into
a societal idea that we all live in the
same kind of temperature we have
automatic garage door openers we have
created this environment where we don't
move and if we're talking about how do
we just make one small change to improve
our mental health that's
exercise hey it's your friend Mel
welcome to the Mel Robins podcast I am
absolutely thrilled that you're here I
am on such a I don't even know what to
say it I feel so excited about what
we're talking talking about today it is
going to be liberating is such an honor
to spend time with you to be together
with you but especially when we're going
to have a conversation that is going to
light you on fire and make you feel both
mad and empowered let's freaking go and
if you're a new listener I want to take
a moment and just welcome you welcome to
the Mel Robbins podcast family and boy
have you picked a winner of a
conversation to listen to because you
made the time to listen to this
particular episode here's what I already
know about you you're the type of person
who values your Health you want the
facts you want the science you want
results and that's what you deserve and
if someone sent this to you that's
really cool it's because they care about
you and they want you to have the
science and the facts and the correct
information so that you can take better
care of yourself too I cannot wait for
you and I to learn from Dr Stacy Sims
today now Dr Sims is a globally
recognized expert in women's health
exercise physiology and nutrition
science she has a PHD in exercise
physiology and nutrition science she's
on the faculty at Stanford teaching
about lifestyle medicine and at Ackland
University of Technology teaching sports
medicine she is a renowned researcher
and has directed research programs at
Stanford Auckland University of
Technology and the University of yat and
she has published check this
out7 peer-reviewed research papers which
in normal persons speak is a a ton her
research has revolutionized how women
mhm women approach Fitness especially
during menopause and hormone changes
she's the author of two groundbreaking
books Roar and the next level she also
has a daughter and just like me is in
her mid-50s juggling a big career a
marriage motherhood and hormone changes
she has so much to teach you today and
we are going to go straight for the Bro
Science we are going to tell you the
mistakes and the lies that you've been
told we're going to tell you the truth
based on the research about what works
for women and what doesn't we're going
to teach you why the things that you've
been doing have been backfiring it's
because you have been exercising like a
dude and it is time for you to exercise
like a woman I am so fired up for you to
be here I am fired up to learn with you
and I am fired up for all of the women
and the young women in your life that
you're going to share this with so
please help me welcome Dr Stacy Sims to
the melro podcast Dr Stacy Sims I am so
thrilled that you're here in our Boston
studios I've been waiting a long time to
be able to sit down meet you and learn
from you I'm just thrilled that you're
here oh thanks for having me I'm excited
have lots of fun and we have a lot to
dig into and so here's where I want to
start could you speak directly to the
person that's
listening and this is somebody who
doesn't have a lot of time but they made
the time yep to be here to learn from
you okay what could that person expect
might change about their life or feel
different if they take everything to
heart that you're about to teach us and
share with us today and they use it in
their own life I find there's two big
things that often happen one most women
become more empowered and have better
body positivity and two they have a
sense of separation from the stress and
their own selves so they're able to take
that step back from the stress of
everything that's happening it's kind of
like that pause moment because when you
are taking care of your body then it
feeds back into a lot of positive
metrics so the big thing that I love is
watching women go through an evolution
to go from being not so confident in
themselves to having such empowerment to
be able to stand up and say I own this
space and I'm taking it you know one
thing that strikes me about your
already is that
you
actually exude that oh thanks now you
have a level of presence and power in
your body and it's not just because you
are in incredibly great shape in terms
of muscle definition
but it's it's actually something that's
noticeable and so I think this goes
beyond sort of that sense of separation
of stress like what I experience in just
sitting here with you is that you're
actually embodied in the present and in
your body and a lot of times when we're
stressed out especially you know as
caregivers and the amount of stuff that
we do we're up in our heads and
disconnected from our body yeah and so
I'm excited to really learn from you
because I want to feel more like the
centered confidence and calmness that
you just seem to move through a space
with I'm good with the facade no just
kidding thanks um yeah it does come from
a lot of pushback I've had in my life so
it's like putting being put into a
pretty Mal dominant situation you have
to find your feet and how do you move
through that space and I found it
through exercise strength all the stuff
that we're going to talk about amazing
so you have such an incredible
background and I'm actually going to
read it because it's quite a bit you
know I've talked about this in when I
was introducing you but you have a PhD
in exercise physiology you're a
researcher you're a former professional
athlete you now trained professional
athletes you're an expert in exercise
physiology you have a long list of other
Specialties like cardiovascular disease
prevention Thermo regulation Women's
Health you are a pioneering researcher
that participates in her own studies and
you have this incredible Mantra Dr
Sims women are not small men yeah what
does that mean yeah um I laugh when
people say women are not small men
because when we hear it we're like oh
yeah that's right but it's started from
when I was teaching at Stanford and
wanted to wake some of the undergrads up
after and lunch and afternoon sleepies
come in and I was teaching about sex
differences in training or high
performance so I would started with
women are not small men and people are
like well of course not like that's you
know women aren't small men but what I
mean by that is everything from what
happens in utero until we die is
different for women than men so when we
talk about women are not small men and
we see all the guidelines that are out
there for exercise all the guidelines
out there for mental health for the
connections the sociocultural pressures
we experience things differently as
women than men do but that's not ever
really explained so when we say women
are not small men it makes people take
that pause and ask well what do you mean
by that what topic so today what I mean
by women are not small men is we're
going to dive into exercise especially
how what we do should change as we move
through our lives what does that motto
women are not small men mean in
practice I think when we look right now
at what's being portrayed in social
media fitness Trends the medical Trends
all of that data is really drawn from
men and just generalized to women which
is a huge disservice so I want women
especially you as a listener on this
podcast to take a pause whenever you see
a new trend come up or someone pushing
something to just go well where do this
originate how does that appropriate for
me as a woman in my phase of life and
when you take that pause you begin to
have an objection to some of the things
that are being pushed on you and and an
objective view of how you should
approach things to make it beneficial
for you I am so glad that we're starting
here because
um I am constantly shocked at the things
that I think I should be
doing and the things that I hear a lot
of male Health experts talking about or
a lot of the Bro Science or a lot of the
kind of bro experts and the Fitness
trends that are very dude oriented no
offense to the guys I'm just saying that
it often has felt like to me as I've
learned more and more like oh my God
wait a minute we've just kind of treated
women and our health almost like if
you're golfing there's the tea That's
further back for the guys and there's
the tea that's a little bit like closer
for the women and we're just going to
treat everybody the same but shrink it a
little bit yep shrink and pink is what
we called it in the industry shrink and
pink shrink and pink so uh we'll take
running shoes or a bicycle all they do
is they make it a little bit smaller
maybe put some pink on it and say it's a
woman's product it's so true I know and
it's like wait that's not really
appropriate you'll see in my book
there's some pink and that's an oage to
shrink in pink because that's what
people think is honoring women by making
it a little bit smaller let's bling it
up with some color and we're going to
call it a woman's product and that is
not appropriate well the other thing
that I think has been like really
fascinating we're going to get into this
is just that a lot of the research has
only been done on men and there hasn't
been research on how certain things have
an impact on women and our hormones and
our body structure and our composition
which is as you've already said
fundamentally different than that of
somebody who's male yeah and so I'm
excited for you to take a step by step
by step and help us kind of tee up all
the assump iions that we've all just
kind of come to assume that work for men
but don't work for women and what we
need to know and need to be doing to
actually work with our bodies and take
better care of ourselves perfect so
what's the most common mistake that
women make by following male Centric
Fitness
advice uh they don't get any results and
they end up what we call tired but wired
I mean if you look at most women who
make a point to get up do some training
go
exercise and it happens so often after
four weeks of following the same kind of
training program as their male partner
their male partner has gotten leaner
fitter better um cognition you know
Focus all of the things that you want
out of fitness and the woman's like how
come I'm fatter and tired and I don't
have any like increase in my fitness
like my partner does and I see it all
the time and I'm always explaining well
one your partner might get up and go
fcet training women's bodies don't
respond well to facet training what's
fcet training I don't even know what the
heck this is like fcet training fcet
training means you're not having any
food before you go do exercise oh so
well that's what I would always do like
I would always literally like I'm going
to eat after because my husband would
eat after and then we would my mouth is
on the floor you can see this on YouTube
but like as you're listening I'm I'm
processing this because I'm thinking how
often I've been pissed off at Chris my
husband yeah because will take on some
challenge together and I'm like this is
not fair like how is it that this is
actually making you lose weight and I
feel like I'm puffier and fluffier and
tired and pissed off yep and I'm
following the same steps I'm doing the
intermittent fasting I'm not eating
beforehand I'm slamming the thing after
I'm doing and I'm like what the hell is
going on and it this is because he's
male and I'm female yep exactly and it
comes really to the brain right so when
we start looking just at first thing you
get up and and our responses are
different where women's Brains will
start going okay where's the food to
come in to help bring my stress hormones
down and get me started for the day okay
and Men by the nature of being XY their
brain's like eh okay I'm going to supply
some amino acids and some blood sugar
and let's get on with the day then we'll
find some food that's fine but women's
brain specifically what we call the
hypothalamus that is really sensitive to
blood sugar and food coming in so if you
get up and you start your your exercise
without any food the hypothalamus is
like wait a second this is a stress to
the body that I need to really try to
figure out but if I don't have food to
counter the fuel that the muscles are
needing from a contraction I need to
find a way to supply that fuel so it
goes into a little bit of a tizzy and
one of the first things that starts to
get broken down is your muscle M cuz
muscle is a pretty active tissue and the
hypothalamus is like well I don't know
if I'm going to be able to supply the
food that this muscle needs if I don't
have any food coming in so it's a very
small amount of food that a woman needs
first thing in the morning to then go be
successful in her training and it's even
if you're going for a walk a lot of
women will get up and go for a walk on
the ospice are you with me like I are
you in my house with me maybe Stacy I'm
I'm sitting here thinking to myself S I
think a lifetime of messaging about like
thin is preferable yeah and that I want
to maximize calories burned so I'm going
to get up and I'm G to have a cup of
coffee because I'm tired and I'm going
to wire myself and then I you know back
in the day would be going for a run or
going to some sort of like Fitness class
uh you know I'm old enough to have been
doing step aerobics and everything else
let's go um
and now and and I've just carried that
over yeah and I also then tell myself a
story that I'm G to get a cramp or I'm
gonna like want to throw up in my mouth
if I'm doing something too much and I've
had too much to eat and so this is a
complete Le different change for me yeah
and it's one that's going to be really
super beneficial so every woman
listening and every woman in your life
if you're listening and your male needs
to know that one of the biggest mistakes
that we're making by following male
Centric Fitness advice is we need as
women biologically and physiologically
speaking to actually have something to
eat first thing when we get up yes yes
and when we start looking at it I've I
did a competition a couple of weekends
ago just for fun and I had so many women
come up and go the first thing that you
did to change my life was to tell me to
eat beforehand and now like my
training's better my outcomes are better
I have more energy and I'm like well of
course cuz your brain is like I can
handle this stress so if you are
supplying fuel to the empty tank of
course you're going to go far if you
think about trying to drive a car and
rev it up and get it on the highway to
at speed with it on E it's not going to
get very far so I try to explain to
women if you're going to get up and even
if you're going for a walk like you want
to maximize what you're doing you want
your metabolism to fire on all cylinders
you want to get some aerobic fitness
through that you need to supply just a
little bit of fuel and it doesn't mean a
full meal it could be the protein coffee
it could be a couple of tablespoons of
yogurt a half a banana it's not a lot
but it's enough to bring your blood
sugar up and tell your brain yeah I I've
got this I've got this so the first
change already small change but critical
one for our biology and Physiology is
you need to eat something before you
move or exercise in the morning yeah and
to also I think like the bigger thing
here for me is that I'm starting to
realize I've been so brainwashed about
the fact that you need to be thin yes
that it's a paradigm shift to actually
think well wait a minute I need to learn
how to work with my body and my natural
wiring to make it work for me and to
actually
optimize the way that my body's designed
as a woman right and one of the things
that um has come up recently in
conversations where uh some women who've
just started into strength training
realm or have dropped all of their you
know big cardio walking because we all
come from the 80s and 90s of let's do 90
minutes of aerobics and and that's not
appropriate so they've gotten out of
that mentality but they'll see other
women at the gym who are on the litical
or treadmill or out running and they
look really lean m and they're like well
I don't understand I kind of want to
look like that but I know that I need to
be doing strength training so I'm
confused the women that are 40 plus who
are doing the cardio for the most part
they're going to be what we call skinny
fat so that means that they're not going
to have a lot of quality muscle there's
going to be a lot of of fatty tissue
within the muscle and their bones are
going to be like chalk because if we are
doing all that cardio work and we're not
looking at how our bodies are aging and
what we need we need the food before the
training we need to put in some strength
training then we're going to
continuously be breaking down the tissue
that we want to keep to age well so when
we're talking about that mentality of
well what do I do it's like these small
steps of yeah let's have some food
before let's look at how we are dosing
our exercise what kinds of intensities
let's bring in some strength training
because all of those are going to feed
forward to having our lean mass having
really strong bones having really good
neuroplasticity so that means how your
brain changes in a positive way so as we
age we don't get dementia so these are
all the things that I would rather women
focus on than the drive from the 9s to
be Kate Moss thin because on the outside
that drive to be super thin is killing
us on the inside wow you you mentioned
protein coffee yeah can you explain what
that is and how that might satisfy the
first takeaway which is eat before you
move in the morning yes so a lot of
women don't have an appetite first thing
in the morning I'm one of those but I
know that I need fuel so I'm very much a
espresso addict I love it and one of the
simple things that I do is I make a
double espresso at night and I mix some
protein powder into my alond milk or
whatever milk you want and then I put
the hot coffee in there and put it in
the fridge overnight and then it's my go
to first thing in the morning where then
I'm getting my 30 gr of protein I'm
getting my caffeine it tastes like a
latte I'm good to go and so that's a
first hit it's a first eating
opportunity to bring in some of that
protein that we need and if you're going
to go do any kind of exercise knowing
that exercise mutes your appetite then
it also helps with that recovery part
because you're going to have those amino
acid circulating your brain's going to
say hey yeah okay I've got stuff to
rebuild tissue so it's a really really
good way of being able to have what you
need without feeling over full and still
enjoying some of the good things of life
like coffee well you've changed my life
already yay because I've got two
takeaways the first one is and I still
want to stay on it so I actually
understand why eating first thing before
I move my body and having fuel first
thing in the morning is actually super
important and I want to unpack that a
little bit more but I want to hover on
the protein coffee because I'm drinking
it right
now you made me one in our studios here
in Boston this is going to change my
life and here's why I have struggled
forever since I've learned and a lot of
us are learning as women that focusing
on more protein and especially getting
protein first thing in the morning is
super important and I'm always
struggling with how the hell am I going
to get 30 grams of protein first thing
in the morning without choking down 10
egg whites and what do I do if I'm on
the go and what do I do if I'm tired of
eggs and what do I do if I don't have a
blender near me and my stuff what do I
like and so you literally took a scoop
of protein shoved it in milk put in
espresso stirred it up and put on ice it
tastes like a freaking milkshake and
what I love about this is that a I can
make it the night before B it's 30 grams
of protein in a cup which c means I
could even take this on the walk with me
I could take this in the car if I'm
dropping my kids off somewhere I could
make this on the road like this is such
an incredible tip so thank you for that
you're welcome what I want to do though
Dr Sims is you mentioned that when women
wake up our brains are different than
the guys and our
stress levels are higher and it is
important to understand that and to give
yourself a little bit of fuel MH what
happens in your
body if you do start eating breakfast in
the morning or you CU a lot of women
skip it a lot of women are now
intermittent fasting a lot of people are
waiting until noon a lot of people don't
want to eat before they exercise because
they don't want cramps or they like
actually want to maximize calorie burn
but what is the benefit to a woman in
particular first thing in the morning if
you give yourself fuel there's a few
things to unpack there so first we look
at eating opportunities because there's
so many women who are one trying to lose
weight or two or in the fitness space
and following some of the trends that
don't eat enough so if you aren't eating
enough you're not going to actually
change your body composition so we look
at eating opportunities first thing in
the morning 30 grams of protein boom
that's an eating opportunity that you're
not really feeling overly full but it's
such a great benefit to the body and
you're ahead of the game by having 30
grams of protein we also look at some of
the newer research that's coming out
about our circadian rhythms or how how
our body goes through 24-hour cycle and
for people who break their fast by
around 8:00 a.m. and then they don't eat
after 6:00 p.m. have all these great
metabolic outcomes that you would expect
from quote intermittent fasting but we
see that people who hold a fast till
noon or after don't get any of that
benefit so if we look well why why is
that we have to understand that half an
hour after a woman wakes up we have a
spike in cortisol that's our stress
hormone if we don't have food to tell
the brain to drop that then we stay in
this heightened stress State and what
cortisol is responsible for is that
fight or flight but also providing fuel
for being able to fight or flight so the
first thing that goes is we start
chewing into our lean mass which is bone
and muscle and a signal to keep our body
fat especially as we start to get older
wait a minute so not eating
and not eating because you think it's
going to help you lose weight actually
counterproductive it's counterproductive
because it's signaling your body to stay
in fight or flight which makes your body
hold on to Fat yes are you kidding me no
I mean when we look at the trends of the
fasted training don't eat be it's all on
male data and the difference between men
and women in the situation is again it
comes down to the brain so a man can get
by with the fasted training because when
when we're looking at getting up and
holding a fast or going training without
food for a man's body it stimulates the
little molecular structures in the
muscles to use more fat because their
muscle structure and the types of fibers
that they have are different than
women's so men have what we call more
glycolytic or fibers that use glucose
and not as many oxidative or the fibers
that use fat as a fuel women we're born
with more of those oxidative fat burning
fibers so when we go and we don't
provide fuel the body's like I'm going
to store fat because I'm going to need
it because that's the preferred fuel for
your muscles so men's bodies will start
to adapt to be able to use more fat
which is why you see fasting and holding
a fast working so well in men but for
women it doesn't do the same because we
have different feedback mechanisms from
the brain we have different muscle
requirements because of different
morphology we call it or different
muscle fiber types so this is where you
know we start looking at all the stuff
that we've been trained to do over the
decades and how counterproductive and
harmful it can be for women who are
trying to improve body composition and
Bone wow now does eating first thing in
the morning because you mentioned the
Circadian rhythm for a woman also help
you sleep better at night absolutely how
come because if we're look looking at
decreasing our overall stress response
so that cortisol bringing the cortisol
down over the course of time you're
going to have a lower Baseline of that
cortisol if you have a lower Baseline of
cortisol then your body can get into
what we call parasympathetic so that's
what you need to sleep if you have this
high elevation of cortisol all the time
we're always sympathetically wired so we
can't get into deep reparative sleep so
you see a lot of Awakenings the other
thing that happens when women frontload
their Foods so we have a lot of of our
calories in the day which we should then
when we go to sleep we aren't waking up
with hypoglycemia that means we're not
waking up with low blood sugar because a
lot of women who undereat or hold a fast
and they aren't eating enough their
Awakenings at night is due to low blood
sugar I thought it was because I had to
pee it's also because of the low blood
sugar Doctor S where the hell have you
been like I I needed you in my life like
decades ago I needed me then too it's
taken me this long to be able to acquire
all the knowledge and the research so
now I'm hoping that we can hit all of
the listeners and so that they will
learn what we should have known decades
ago this is so eye opening like already
you
have highlighted so many differences
between men and women just in the
morning just in the stress levels just
in the fuel that we need in the morning
in the muscle comp composition like all
of it and it also is very Illuminating
because it makes a lot of sense then as
to why the programs that work for Chris
and seem to work like magic actually
leave me frustrated and tired yeah so
what would be the ideal breakfast for
anyone whether like and let's just talk
about the person who just wants to move
more they want to take better care of
their body they want to understand how
their body works so that you're getting
better results and you're feeling better
in your life so what would breakfast
look like just on an average morning if
you know for anybody yeah that I will
say that it's a hard one because people
have different food preferences how
about an avatar what's an avatar a a
makeup person okay a makeup person
makeup person so we'll say there's a
woman who is plant-based but not
vegetarian know so she has a preference
for plants three kids you know super
busy wakes up has been waking up tired
but wired didn't sleep well was like
okay I need to make this change never
hungry in the morning so we can split
her breakfast it could be overnight oats
which is chiaia seeds oatmeal some um
milk or or oat milk to soak it then when
she gets up she's like I'm going to
split that in half the first half I'm
going to add some berries and maybe
another tablespoon of Greek yogurt CU
then I'm going to get some protein
carbohydrate some Fiber and it's going
to calm me down it's going to tell my
brain yep ready to go okay then
you either are going out for your walk
maybe you're going to do some home
strength training maybe you're meeting a
friend for a session maybe you're taking
15 minutes of Just Breath work to to
bring yourself down especially if you're
the Avatar of three kids in a busy life
just taking that moment to put yourself
first and then when you get back maybe
it's an hour hour and a half later you
have the second half the second half of
those overnight oats with a few more
tablespoons of Greek yogurt and some
nuts and berries because then you're
getting the protein carbohydrate so
you've actually split your breakfast but
you've given your body the benefit of
food on different eating opportunities
without being over full but at the end
you end up with 30 grams of protein over
the course of a couple of hours so it's
easy you can mix it up do it the night
before you know that I'm not that hungry
but if I have a little bit and then over
the course of a couple of weeks you're
going to find that you're going to wake
up go yeah I need some food and this is
kind of a reset of your circadian rhythm
your body is starting to fall in line
your hypothalamus is understanding your
appetite hormones are starting to work
properly and when all of that feeds
forward then you're going to start to
see changes in body composition because
you're having better sleep because we
can't change anything if our sleep is
perturbed so the more we focus on how
are we going to work with our body's
natural rhythms and the way that our
hormones work the the more it feeds into
better parasympathetic drive for better
sleep I have just so screwed this up
like I literally wake up I delay the
coffee I exercise on an empty stomach I
then have my coffee which I'm then
drinking on an empty stomach which means
I've now maximized stressing myself out
and then I'm slamming something that has
30 45 grams of protein after I work out
and so what have you done if you are the
kind of person like I am that you've
bought into all the BS and you've
basically been starving yourself in the
morning and even if you get out for a
walk how are you kind of actually not
only not getting the benefit but you're
making it worse what's happening in like
the person's body when you do not feed
yourself first thing in the morning as a
woman yeah I always bring it down to
what are we doing when when we want to
exercise right we're looking for better
blood glucose control we're looking for
better bone we're looking for better
muscle if you're not eating then you are
not going to get better at any of that
stuff because the body again is like I
need fuel for the stress that's
occurring and I need fuel for the
exercise so if you've been brainwashed
like I am MH and you're exercising
because you are trying to like lose
weight or you're trying to look thin
MH what is happening if I continue to go
down that route where I don't eat before
I exercise and I'm basically starving
myself and I'm going for my walk and I'm
delaying food you lose muscle and then
the other thing when we look at women
who are late 30s early 40s onwards we
get a signal to put on more visceral fat
so that's that deep belly fat that that
metabolically active that can be
dangerous so I'll see women who are at
you know doing the same Pursuit and
really proud of the fact that they're
intermittent fasting they're not
breaking their fast till noon they've
had their coffee to hold them through
and you do a DEA and what's a DEA a DEA
is when you go and you get a complete
body scan so it looks at your muscle it
looks at fat where Fat's put it looks at
how dense your bones are so we see their
dexa results and on the outside they
look healthy right but on the inside
it's a bit of a scary story where we see
low bone density we see an increase of
fat accumulating in the belly area which
means that it's more what we call
metabolically active so you see a change
in your um cholesterol so you have more
of the quote bad cholesterol that's
elevated you have more inflammatory
markers which is a predisposition for
diabetes we see insulin resistance so I
know that there are listeners and maybe
you know you're thinking about well I've
been doing this forever and I don't have
any bad blood markers what's going on I
didn't say that it necessarily comes out
that's the worst case scenario but when
we look at what's happening on the
inside side I don't want your bones to
be like chalk and I don't want you not
to have muscle to be able to get up and
run after your grandkids or carry your
groceries into your house so if we just
make that Small Change by having some
food first thing and then carrying on
with your day you're going to get the
impetus to build muscle you're going to
get the impetus to keep your bone and
you're going to be able to reduce the
signaling for that deep belly fat and
it's all those Health like I understand
it I've been there I grew up in that
same 1980s 1990s and I still get it in
my head sometimes like well is this the
right thing and I'm I've done the
research I've been in the lab I've
implemented it so it is really difficult
to get your head around yeah but you
have to look at the long terms like
where do you want to be in 5 years 10
years 15 years from now well and I also
think it's just like if you actually are
working out not only to take care of
yourself but because you do want to
change the composition of your body you
do want to be a little leaner you do
want to be stronger that focusing on the
actual science and this is like a
complete turnaround for me that you need
to actually eat more yes in order to
lose exactly which is the exact opposite
of the brainwashing that all women and
girls have have received for their
entire life right and so it's so helpful
to hear you talk about the science and
it makes so much sense because I think
we've all had that experience in our
life we're like I am trying and this
isn't working right and the first
mistake that I've been making for now 56
years I'm understanding is literally not
eating before I exercise yeah and you
know one thing I want to ask is does
this work for everyone you know I got
this listener question because when
people found out that you were coming oh
my God it was like our website crashed
Ruby wrote in why do some people have
natural muscle tone and some of us can
eat right work out and we are still
flabby and not
toned there are lots of things on this
and I wish that Ruby was in this room
because then I could say well let's look
at um your morphology so your body type
so there are some women who have a
better predisposition for building
muscle we call those mesomorphic and
then we have other women who struggle
really hard to put muscle Mass on and
they tend to be a little bit flaber and
that is more of our endomorphic and then
we have in the middle the ectomorphic
that are the super skinny K moss and
most of the time people are a mix of
that okay so when we look at those
different muscle types and you're
looking at doing all the work and not
getting any benefit I want to see what
kind of training you're doing because if
we are looking at when you're eating and
how you're complimenting your exercise
then we can make gains and every woman's
a little bit different like my sister
she isn't so into Athletics and stuff
that I am we grew up in the same
household but I was always out building
tree forts and she was in reading books
uhhuh but over the past year she's
really put herself into getting stronger
and strength training body composition
is changing her grip strength is
stronger and she's like I never really
thought that lifting weights would help
me change my body composition I was like
why have you not thought of that like if
if you're lifting under load you build
muscle she's like but then that's weight
on the scale and I was always afraid of
the weight on the scale not the outcome
of looking better right and then we also
because we've been so gaslit to think
that it's about being so thin right that
and that's what's desirable that you
hear build muscle and you're like but I
don't want to bulk up I'm actually
trying to lean down yeah and what you're
saying is no no no this is actually like
putting on your own Spanx with your
muscles right it tightens you up right
and I will say like I sit here and I
know people always comment about my
arms and it takes a lot of work to get
arms like that I would think yeah but
the other thing is I they're amazing
arms thanks I I'm wearing a long sleeve
shirt for a
reason if I had your arms I'd be wearing
a tank top too I would love it if all of
this would go lower body like I have
tried for years to get really strong
hamstrings and really strong glutes
they're strong but they're not bulky
it's just mesomorphic up here
ectomorphic down so it's the difference
in the
combination um but I went through a time
where I was really upset with the fact
that I had more muscle like when I was
bike racing I tried really really hard
to lose it but I couldn't because my
body's like no this is how you are born
so women who are like I'm really trying
to build muscle it doesn't necessarily
mean you're going to get bulky
if you don't have a genetic
predisposition for putting muscle on
really really easily it's really hard to
get bulky and for most women who are
trying to put muscle on not eating or
doing lots of cardio work you're not
going to put muscle on it's really hard
to get
bulky so what do you want everyone to
know about exercise as opposed to diet
ah so when we look at all the diet
trends that are out there right we see
the plant face the carnivorous the keto
the intermittent fasting all of the
things they are born out of a Want For
Better Health body composition better
gut all of those things but if you
exercise then you get all of those
things and wait say that again yeah okay
so hold on a second so all of those
diets are designed to try to create a
health outcome through eating yes but if
you exercise the exercise provides the
health outcome yes because we look at
exercis as a stress like we have gotten
into a societal idea that we all live in
the same kind of temperature we have
automatic garage door openers we have
the internet we have our computers even
driverless cars so we have created this
environment where we don't move the
outcome of having a environment where we
don't move we don't have a lot of green
space or opportunities to even walk
places is now we have this obesity
epidemic and even if you're not facing
obesity you're facing some
overweightness and you're being
bombarded by all these diet
Styles if we were just to put a pause on
the diet style and just take a step back
and say you know what if I go back to
eating normally which means that I'm
eating breakfast lunch dinner and I'm
not eating snacks after dinner and I'm
kind of paying attention to kind of food
that I'm eating so it's nutrient dense
it's not all these ultr processed things
there's no protein Pop-Tarts CU it says
protein on it you know what I call this
Dr Sims the grandparent diet yes okay
basically how your grandparents lived
right exactly and then you put in some
exercise because exercise is a stress
the body is very adaptable to stress so
if we're looking at doing a longer
harder walk up a hill after a couple of
weeks of doing that it's going to be
easy cuz your body's adapted to that
stress oh we call it getting fitter but
actually your body has adapted all of
its mechanisms to that stress so if
we're looking at how do I get a better
okay hold on a second so I just had this
like Epiphany okay I can't believe how
many bombs you're dropping today like I
I I I've never thought about exercise
that way because I've focused on you
have to exercise to get in better shape
what you're saying is exercise is
intentionally moving and stressing your
body in a way that it needs and is
designed to do yeah and in response to
the stress your body gets stronger at
being able to manage stress exactly oh
my God it's a stress resilience and the
reason why we're so flabby and
everything else is because we're sitting
around and not moving and not stressing
our bodies in the way that we need to
and that only makes us more stressed out
right because we look at stress mental
health all of the things that are really
plaguing everyone and the part of it is
lack of community lack of empathy all of
these things that breed depression
mental health and the fact that we
aren't moving our bodies there's so much
research out there that says if you go
for a walk you're you are reducing
stress if you go for a walk and you
actually go to a green space so that's
to a park and you're in nature it
induces an incredible parasympathetic
response which means that you reduce
stress but because we are so ingrained
to doing all the things all the time
inside sitting and not actually getting
outside having the fresh air having that
connection with being outside and moving
our bodies we are by Design now a global
of very stressed out unempathetic
depressed people and if we're talking
about how do we just make one small
change to improve our mental health
that's exercise I'm not necessarily here
as an exercise physiologist to tell you
the listener to go out and go for a long
hard walk because you want better body
composition I'm here as an exercise
physiologist to explain what exercise is
it is an incredible positive stress on
the body that creates changes from
central nervous system down to the
smallest little thing in your cell to
improve your overall stress resilience
and Metabolism meaning how your body
handles food how your brain reacts to
stress how your brain perceives an
environment and you just the moving part
really does help bring Center and bring
yourself back to you I believe it and I
want to see if I can
just use an example to try to to really
paint the picture of what you're
teaching us right now which is an
entirely different way to think about
the importance of movement and exercise
strength training whatever it is that
you're going to do MH when you go for a
walk and let's say you go for a walk and
you were mentioning you go for a walk
and there's a hill in your neighborhood
and when you have to go up the hill
we've all experienced this you get
shortness of breath you got to be using
your legs a little bit more to go up the
incline mhm make it a little winded a
little sweaty yep even if you got a dog
on a leash pulling you up the hill like
you're going and that is you by
exercising your body putting yourself in
a stressful situation right because it's
requiring your body to exert effort and
to move against that incline and it's
designed to do that yeah and if you keep
doing that over time what you're
actually doing in addition to all the
positive things that happen is you're
training your
body on how to be strong in situations
that are stressful right so the more
that you walk and the more that you
build muscle and the more that you take
the advice that you're about to give us
about what we should specifically be
doing as women fast forward six months
from now if you keep doing that and
you're sitting in a stressful meeting at
work the impact of that outside stress
on you is going to be way less because
you and your life have been
strengthening your body by going to the
gym and going for a walk so that your
body can actually be in stressful
situations and not get hijacked exactly
so the whole flight or fight response
that people talk about with cortisol
we're flighting we're teaching our body
that flight by exercising and your
body's like this is a stress I need to
understand it overcome it get stronger
could also think about it as the fight
response too cuz if you're in the gym
and you're building the muscle and
you're ready to go coiled up ready to go
your body's learning that stress because
it's we're not an algorithm we adapt to
so many different things so if we put
our body into an uncomfortable or a
challenged situation doesn't like it so
it learns how to overcome that and get
stronger in the process so when I you
know as you're explaining it's like yes
it's all about stress resilience we're
resilient to stress in a meeting our
immune system is also really resilient
to stuff that's going around and we're
also resilient enough to maintain a
focus if we're getting ready to lose it
and our kid goes off like we're not
going to break down and start yelling at
our partner or our kid because we have
the stress resilience we're able to take
that
pause it makes so much sense and you
know you've talked a lot about strength
training why is strength training so
important for women in
particular yeah I wish I had known about
strength training way back when like I
was introduced to it when I was 16
because my friend's brother was a
bodybuilder and I was like oh okay I'll
go cuz Michelle you're going I'll go
with you but I didn't really realize
what that meant so when we talk about
the science of strength training right
now we know that with age we lose muscle
really quickly start to lose it when we
hit 30 and it's really important because
one it's an active tissue so it helps
maintain so many different systems in
our body not only that but we think
about strength training and how it um
puts leverage on the bone to improve
bone but the big thing really is when we
think about cognitive decline so we see
that there's a sex difference as we get
older in Alzheimer's dementia cognitive
decline and it has to do with brain
brain metabolism so that's the fuel that
your brain uses and what we call
neuroplasticity or how your brain
adapts and creates neural Pathways if
we're strength training then we yeah
we're taking care of our bone and a
muscle but it's creating signals to the
brain to increase its ability to be
really plastic so it's like yeah okay I
need to have a new PA pathway let's
develop that pathway and so it's always
changing it's like sidoku right you're
mentally working on that but strength
training does the same thing but it also
Improv improves overall metabolism so
now your brain is very flexible and it's
like okay well I need glucose but then I
can use lactate so when you start doing
all of these things it reduces your
chances of developing cognitive issues
so for women I'm always like yeah
strength training is great because we're
building all these things we're changing
our body composition but for the long
term we want to have a good body and a
good mind so for doing these things and
creating more Pathways and
developing existing Pathways and making
the brain very responsive and able to be
flexible then we're going to have a
really good sound mind when we're all
doing Zimmer frame races when we're 100
what are Zimmer frame races you know
those frames that old women have to use
and or old men I've never seen those I
don't know what you're talking about in
the nursing homes you haven't seen those
silver Walkers oh yes I thought that was
a game you were talking about so the I
have a feeling you're not going to be
using a walker I have a feeling you're
going the one teaching us all how to
lift weights when we're 90 years old in
the nursing home together well no I'll
be using a Zimmer frame I'll be doing
the races with everyone else because I
can't say that my joints are all that
great so what is the biology behind
building muscle and how is it different
for men versus women like what do women
need to know women are what we call more
fatigue resistant so as I was describing
earlier the differences in the muscle
fiber types right so women have more of
those fat burning we call endurant
fibers so that means that you can do
lots of work and then you recover
relatively quickly so when we're looking
at sets and Reps and things like that
women don't need as much recovery time
between your sets and Reps to be able to
have the same kind of training stress
now break that down please because I
don't know anything that you just talked
about I was like sets reps okay what are
we doing so say have a man and a woman
that go to the gym and they're like okay
I'm supposed to do five sets so that's
five sets so yeah this is there a lot I
know it's an avatar here okay well let's
just use an avatar of somebody who is
just starting okay so like we're gonna
like what's the bare minimum doctors I'm
looking for something I can succeed at
five sets sounds like a lot yeah I'll
get to there but I want I wanted to
explain the biology okay you tell me
biology I'll give you the biology and
then I'll give you the actionable where
to start thank you Dr SS all right so if
we take a man and a woman they go to the
gym and they have this the similar
program where they're supposed to do
five sets of five reps on the three
minutes so what does that mean you do
five reps of a squat in 3 minutes so
however long it takes you to do those
and then you rest the rest of the time
for the 3 minutes okay so maybe it takes
you 30 seconds to do your five squats
and then you have 2 minutes and 30
seconds to recover oh okay okay and you
do that five times so that's 5 by five
so if a man and a woman both do that and
we look over time the strength the
relative strength gain so that means
relative to sex and body weight the man
will acquire better strength gains in a
woman but if we were to change that
recovery for the woman to go five sets
on 5x5 on the 2 minute so she does it in
30 seconds and has a minute 30 recovery
then over course of time she'll have the
same outcomes because her body is like I
don't need as much rest so it starts to
kind of downturn with so much rest so
you can put more training stress on and
less time as a woman wow so this is one
of the things that we're starting to
really discover in the strength training
research because it's relatively new
we're like okay we know that there's the
sex differences in the muscle fiber
types where women have more of these you
know endurant type fibers men have more
of the fast glycolytic fibers so if we
really want to maximize the outcome of
our strength training we need to work to
women's physiology where they don't need
as much rest to get the same kind of um
stress and outcome and you know what I
like about that it means it doesn't take
as much time exactly I have a lot of
time so that's very good news Dr Sims
you know I'm about to ask you a bunch of
questions about like the specifics of
what we should be doing but I had one
question you know whenever I'm
complaining about uh my body or you know
feeling out of shape or whatever it is
that I want to change my husband always
turns me and says well don't forget abs
are built in the kitchen not in the gym
yeah is this like a man's is that what
works for men that works for men
definitely yep because when I hear that
abs are built in the kitchen not in the
gym I'm like am I supposed to starve
myself like what what are you talking
about right so this comes back to the uh
you know the fasting and I get really
frustrated where men will drop alcohol
they'll drop sugar and then all of a
sudden their abs are ripped right they
like belly fat gone yes but for women we
tend to store belly fat correct and if
I'm not drinking yeah I want results I
know but it doesn't necessarily happen
no it doesn't Dr Sims it doesn't this is
not fair no cuz I don't understand my
own body I know it's very frustrating
and I've been listening to the Bro
Science and my stupid husband telling me
the advice that works for him and he's
he's only trying to help so what do I so
why does it not work that way for women
we have a higher percent body fat for
one and again it comes down to food
intake and hypothalamus so if we start
taking out food and not replacing those
calories with something else then we end
up in a lower energy state so that's a
that could be a whole another podcast
but basically we're not eating enough to
support body composition change and
health outcomes so if we talk about ABS
in the kitchen if we're eating the same
kind of grandparent diet then we're
going to have the same outcomes right
but if we have the extra 20 bit of life
where we're having chocolate and whiskey
and all those fun things a man can take
it out and get super ripped woman takes
it out there's no
change why because the hypothalamus is
like where are those calories I need
those calories so if we want to eat a
little bit cleaner we have to make sure
that we're actually providing enough
calories so if we're providing enough
calories and our body's like yep sweet
we got enough for all the things that we
need to do in a day overcome the stress
and we have enough to uh fuel the
training and the changes we want with
the exercise we're doing you're going to
get those abs wow and then the compound
movements like working abs in a
functional way not doing sit-ups but
like doing deadlifts or squats where you
have to use your abs as a support
mechanism builds them faster than you
see you know guys on the floor doing
lots of sit-ups or rushing twist yeah
they're going to get those strong ABS
but for women it's better to do this
compound for that torsion to be able to
use that as support because then it
allows us to stand upright and have
better posture because our center of
gravity is down in our hips men's center
of gravity is up in their chest so if
we're working to control our posture and
develop the strength through our core
and we're standing up taller our ABS
show wow cuz I I would be a happy woman
if I never had to do a crunch again and
so if I'm actually lifting that could be
true so let's talk about the specific
things we should be doing okay what is
the minimum amount of exercise that a
woman needs to maintain her health and
to be strong if we are looking from an
age standpoint okay okay let's start
with our 20s in our 20s you can get away
with a lot right what does that mean so
that means that you could do bare
minimum couple of days a week of mixed
aerobic and strength training so you
don't have to do that much okay so it
could be a total body circuit set twice
a week and that means like going to the
gym and doing the machines you could do
that or you could do an at home circuit
where you can do what I say every every
minute on the minute so you warm up with
stretches and Mobility for five or so
minutes and then you have five minutes
where one minute is jumping lunges the
next minute might be some push-ups the
third minute might be um some overhead
thrust or you know you're pushing
something overhead the fourth minute
might be some air squats and then the
fifth minute is completely off where
you're recovering you do that circuit
two or three times that's all you need
wow and you don't even need equipment no
that's your bare minimum right because
we're talking bare minimums and talk to
me about cardio because we've all been
so obsessed with cardio so is cardio a
good thing is it a bad thing so cardio
is interesting because it's about
intensity so if we're talking about
going for a walk that's really good like
you're walking with a friend perfect
because that's going to allow you to
have some metabolic change it's going to
improve your blood glucose it's going to
improve your body stress resilience and
hey you get to hang out with a friend so
that's great it's Community it's
connection it's all the great things so
that's one kind of cardio if we're
looking at improving our blood pressure
you can do some walking but what we find
is true high-intensity work that's uh
really directed with call it Sprint
interval training where it's 30 seconds
or less as hard as you can go and it
doesn't have to be running it could be
kettle bell swings could be air squats
jumping lunges could be running could be
cycling anything that's going to make
you go as hard as you can for 30 seconds
or less and recover for two minutes you
might do two or three of those and that
is such a strong stress that it creates
this whole Cascade of change that
improves your entire cardiovascular
system okay so let me make sure I'm
tracking so one thing that you would
tell us to do
is to do Sprint training which sounds
horrible but it actually as you broke it
down was like oh I could do that yeah 30
seconds or less of something that's high
intensity whether you're sprinting on a
treadmill or you're doing kettle ball
swings or you're doing push-ups or
you're doing jumping jacks or just
something right and then you rest for a
minute and a half minute and a half to
two minutes because we want a full
recovery from it's more of a central
nervous system recovery because we want
to be able to go just as hard if not
harder for the next interval and then
how many of those am I doing so you
don't want to do any more than five oh I
love the minimum that's it yeah I can do
that that's the maximum five is the
maximum now we're talking Dr Sims some
people will go I can do all five and
then they start and if they're doing it
properly after two they're like I can't
do anymore that's fine you've gotten
that impetus of stress and it creates
this whole Cascade where all of a sudden
your muscles are releasing signals
called myocin that now is telling your
liver let's not store that visceral fat
we need the that fat for other things
it's also telling your body we don't
want to store Under the Skin
subcutaneous fat we need that fat for
other things it's also telling your
muscles to open up and bring
carbohydrate in so our insulin become or
we become more sensitive to insulin so
there's so many great things about that
high high intensity and by the way your
blood vessels are going to respond
really well so you get better blood
vessel compliance vasod dilation
constriction so better blood pressure
control because again your body responds
to stress and it's such a strong stress
your body's like there's this whole
Myriad of things that I need to be able
to do to do that stress again so it's a
really effective means of getting heart
health better metabolic health and
better body composition and burning fat
in 30 seconds of effort yeah I mean I I
am G to I actually going to do that good
that sounds like something because when
you were going the box I'm like I think
I can absolutely do that and again I
also love that it doesn't take a lot of
time no I mean I come from a huge
endurance background but now I'm tra
like I live in New Zealand I'm traveling
the world I have a daughter I have a
business super busy and I still want to
exercise because one it helps with
stress resilient two yeah I'm like you
know there's a little Aesthetics and
vanity in there of course and Sprint
interval it's so between lifting three
days a week and some Sprint training
that's pretty much what I do because
that's all I have time for lifting three
days a week MH and that Sprint training
we just heard of 30 second bursts full
recovery for a minute and a half to two
minutes and try to do it five times
maximum yep and sometimes I put that on
the end of my strength training because
if I'm already at the gym I might finish
with some aerodine bike you know 30
seconds as hard as I can go so I'm
maximizing time so I don't spend any
more than 45 minutes to an hour in the
gym so if you had to bottom line what a
woman should be doing in her 20s versus
her 30s versus or 40s versus 50s and up
what would it be so strength training
across the board okay the type of
strength training you do is different so
when we're in our 20s and our early 30s
we can do some of the protocol stuff
that that is out there for men like
you're doing your 10 to 12 reps or
you're going to failure or you're going
in you're doing a full body workout
you're going to get results as we start
to get into our mid-30s and onward we
start to have changes in our estrogen
progesterone and it doesn't quite work
for us okay because now we need to find
an external stress that's going to
create the same responses that those
hormones used to support okay so now we
want to look at more of a power-based
type training what does that mean yeah
like 30 up your hormones change and now
the 10 to 12 reps that we've all been
socialized
does not work is why we all start
bitching about the fact that our bodies
are not responding to what we always
used to do this makes a lot of sense Dr
Sims so when you're doing the higher
reps it's more of what we call metabolic
stress so that's more like muscle
contraction using fuel yeah but it's not
an impetus to build lean mass or to
become stronger so this is where I say
the power base so when we're talking
about the spectrum of weights and and
and the reps and sets and stuff power
based is zero to six to eight reps oh I
love that I can do less yes but it has
to be heavy okay has to be heavy but
okay yeah so that means that you go and
you pick up say we pick up this 20 right
and you're like oh yeah I can do 10
overhead no problem maybe I could do two
more great so we call that 10 with two
reps in reserve okay we want you to be
at a six with two reps in reserve so
that means I would have you put the 20
down and pick up those 30s and see can
you do six really good wow not failing
form and then could you eek out two more
great that's the weight that we want you
to use gotcha so I'm definitely lifting
way too
light and I am lifting far too much of
it like the little tiny two pound
weights with the put those down put
those down like those aren't doing
anything for my chicken wing arms no no
not at all okay not at all well that
explains it because I'm like why does
this hurt so much and I'm getting zero
result here yeah but my daughter's
literally look like they're cut yeah wow
cuz they respond well to metabolic
stress as our bodies get older we need
more of a central nervous system Goa so
the general takeaway here is that when
we hit that sort of late 30s to 40s Mark
and our estrogen is dropping and our
bodies are changing and we're not
getting the same results you got to
really focus on these Sprint trainings
and also doing weight training where the
load is heavier but the reps are are
shorter yeah but I don't want women who
are listening to go oh I heard Mel's
podcast and I have to go lift these
heavy weights and do Sprint training it
takes time yeah to learn how to do
things well without getting injured
because I mean when we get older we're
more susceptible to soft tissue injury
joint injuries so I always want women to
learn how to move first so if you've
never done any kind of strength training
don't be put off by oh I heard I have to
lift heavy weights I better not do at
all no any kind of resistance is good
maybe it's just body weight at the start
maybe you're doing a body weight circuit
and then maybe you're putting a backpack
with some stuff that's in there to make
it a little bit heavier maybe you're
following somebody online that's
teaching you how to move properly first
and over the course of time you can add
load because your body is learning how
to move and it's becoming stress
resilient so you add load to increase
that stress and then over the course of
six to eight months you're going to be
in lifting heavy weights and doing the
Sprints without injury so it's not a
training block like we've all been
conditioned to what do I do every day in
and out in and out so I can get X
results we want to think about what am I
doing to improve my overall health my
strength my bones my brain so that when
I'm 80 I'm self-sufficient when I'm 90
I'm self-sufficient it's not a training
Block it's a lifestyle that we want in
so it takes time to build into that
lifestyle so I another question from a
listener named Aaron is it better to use
machines or free
weights with machines I want people to
realize that it's hard for a woman to
actually get the machines to fit well
because they are designed for a 58 to 6
foot guy who's 160 to 190 lbs so if you
are outside of that Norm it's really
hard to get the right fit which can
predispose you to
injury if if you are just getting
started it can be a way because you're
not going to put a lot of load on you're
not going to get as injured like I'm not
for me personally I'm not a huge fan of
something like Planet Fitness but I do
appreciate the fact that they've opened
the doors to so many people to make
lifting accessible so a woman can go in
and use their machine circuit and get
some resistance and some load to start
to get them self resilient so then they
can move away from those machines and
get into to dumbbells I like more of the
free weights where you have a barbell or
a dumbbell because you have to use more
of your stabilizing muscles which is how
we move anyway because you're not going
to go pick up a bag of groceries just
with your arm right so if you're looking
at um bicep curls or tricep dips on a
machine that's not functional per se yes
you're adding load but I like it when
people are okay I've got to lift the
groceries or I've got to lift this
overhead so I'm going to do a full squat
using my abs and I'm going to go from
ground to overhead it could be with a
plate could be with a dumbbell it could
just be that motion at start because we
have to think about how we move in the
day I would love to have you talk
directly to the person listening who has
never stepped foot in a gym because I do
think you know even though I'm in shape
and I know a little bit about what I
should be doing I always feel
intimidated when I go to a gym
because there's always guys like it's
filled with guys yep and there's more
and more women which is great but if I
walk into a gym even at a hotel and I'm
seeing all the machines and then I see
the free weight space and then I see the
little space over and I don't know
exactly what I should be doing right I
don't stay long and I leave and I would
love to have you since you've been in
this industry for so long talk to the
person who wants to do something and
wants to learn about this but the idea
of actually walking into the local gym
is just daunting yep so what do you want
them to know though about the people at
the front desk
and the way that people at a gym think
about somebody new Walking In yeah so
gyms are super gendered I sometimes get
intimidated you do yeah so I'll say like
if I go to a typical bro gym like a
Gold's Gym mhm I'll walk in and I'll see
the lifting platforms and there's some
big dudes and I'm like uh maybe I'll
come back I'll go do something else
first so it's it's still there because
the gems are so gendered and it's a
fault of that industry where you walk in
as a woman the front desk person looks
at you and goes oh okay how much weight
do you want to lose here's the cardio
machines here are our classes if a guy
walks in they're like yo bro how much
weight do you want to put on how much
muscle the lifting platforms are back
there and we have bumper plates and our
dumbbells go up to 80 lbs so you know
it's all back there but it's so gendered
even if you feel like I'm going to go to
the free weights because you have to
walk through all the treadmills and the
ellipticals and cardio and then you like
the free weights are here and then the
lifting platforms are at the back yes so
it's not surprising that someone who's
not ever been in a gym situation doesn't
want to go into a gym situation
and the way that we can get started in
this is put the gem out out of your head
at the moment right so we can look at
there are two main things that allow
women to thrive in strength training one
is knowing what to do and two is
community right we see that working out
with someone else is fun for one thing
and two it allows you to push yourself a
little bit harder it's just
intrinsically you want to keep up or you
don't want to look like the weak link
it's just a psych psychological things
so Community working working out with
someone is super important so if you're
someone who's like I don't want to go to
the gym I don't know what to do well we
can look at some of the online things
that are out there so like if you're
really super super basic and you want
someone to work with maybe oneon-one or
maybe a small group you could look to
someone like Loretta hog who does
Loretta loves lifting she's very like
she trains her mom she trains other
people who are just trying to really
understand how to do stuff in their
house it's a very basic way of starting
and you can move forward from there if
you're someone who's like I got that
part but I want to work out with a
friend and we want to set program then
maybe you look at someone like the Betty
rocker where she has specific programs
where we can work out with her in her
community or you and a friend can work
out together and that's a way to do more
stuff with dumbbells in the house then
we can move forward and go to something
like Haley happens Fitness that I've
partnered with where it's from the gym
where you actually have an app that
shows you what to do you can go into the
gym you know exactly what machines or or
barbell or dumbbells to use you bring in
a friend you can both do it together so
you're like here's my app this is what I
do you can record everything keeps
progress and you know exactly what to do
and it's guided for 12 weeks and it's
Progressive overload so you get benefit
there's lots of conversations there's
lots of community around it or you can
even look if you're really confident and
you're like yep I got that too I want to
get straight to barbell with some
dumbbell then you can look at something
like Annie tourist daughters Empower
which has a page from Crossfit so
there's all sorts of levels that you can
find and the big thing is grab a friend
have a friend and have that ownership to
say for 20 minutes let's meet have our
conversation and do this together
because we're going to get strong
together and it's fun I've been trying
to get my daughter engaged in some
strength training stuff and she's 12 we
have a project coming up where she needs
to know how to move properly and I have
her working with one of my friends in a
high performance gym but it's not
lifting it's moving and having fun so
she has another little friend in there
who's a surfer and a soccer player just
like she is and they go there and they
have fun she came back first day fizzing
going I didn't know how fun it could be
at the gym especially when you have a
friend I'm like exactly it's the adult
playground but little kids are being EXP
go to it it's like come into my
playground a playground it is absolutely
a playground where else can you like
jump up and down on things and then like
there's a rope and you can pull the Rope
or there's a sled and you can push and
pretend you're a bear or whatever it is
it doesn't matter everyone's there
sweating everyone's there doing stuff
it's like make it time to play don't
make it something that you're like I
don't want to go this is too hard and I
appreciate the list of resources and
we'll make sure to link to those in the
show notes so I have a bunch of burning
questions that listeners submitted okay
and we may have covered some of this but
I'm just going to hit these so that I
make sure to cover the things that keep
people kept writing in about that they
wanted you to answer Dr Sims okay can
you talk about cold plunging sure should
women be doing it what are the mistakes
that we're making what's the difference
between men and women and cold plunging
so inherently women don't need as cold
so thank you we don't no why when we're
looking at stress response cuz that's
how I view all the environmental and
exercise things is what kind of stress
it puts on the body when a woman gets
into ice cold or cold water and gets in
there it invokes such a severe strong
stress response much stronger than a
male's response that her body goes into
uh more of a shutdown phase where it
invokes a sympathetic dve and it doesn't
create the metabolic changes that we see
with men if you were to take a woman and
put her in 15 or 16 Celsius which is
around that 55 degree Mark she'll end up
with the same responses that a man has
because it's not a severe shock to a
woman's body as it is for a man's why is
that because we have more body fat so we
tend to vasod dilate and Vaso constrict
first for controlling our temperature We
Men will Vaso constrict and sweat when
they're cold no we're talking about just
in general okay so if we're taking a
woman and putting her in ice the body's
first response to environmental change
is severe oaso constriction and with
women with rain odds we have a stronger
constriction response because it's a
protective mechanism for men they'll
constrict and then start shivering to
induce heat women will just constrict if
we put ourselves into that 55 to 60
degree water or 15 to 16 C will
constrict and then start shivering so
we'll get the same benefit it's just the
ice is too cold for us to start that
shivering so we need the Shivering for
thermogenesis to get some of those
responses so we don't need ice we need
cool water I have been doing this all
wrong and do you feel uncomfortable when
you get in the ice well I I I mean I
live in southern Vermont so there's
always like an ice slick on the thing
and you're like having to take an Axe
and you know cut up the top of the
barrel or keep an agricultural bubbler
in it to keep it from freezing it's it's
got to be at least 32 degrees Yeah too
cold and my husband gets in it and he's
like a freaking like meditation Zen he
just gets in sits down he starts
shivering I climb in that sucker and I'm
like and then I can barely breathe I
never shiver right and the Shivering is
what you're supposed to be doing in
there yes because shivering is an
automatic uh response for survival
because when we're shivering we're
increasing metabolic heat so we're able
to keep our core temperature elevated so
we don't die and it's a strong response
that the body has to cold for women when
we're Vaso constricting and we're trying
to hold heat in we don't have the
capacity because water on the cold skin
is pulling out the heat so fast that the
body is just getting colder and colder
and colder and we won't really start
shivering when it's that cold so when
we're looking at like if you get in the
ice it's way colder than if you get into
a plunge pool that's cold so if we have
4 plunge pool 4 de Celsius so that's
about 38 Fahrenheit and you sit there
in a little microclimate and you don't
move at all you'll create a warm bubble
around you and then you might start to
shiver so that's what we say if you fall
through the ice and you're trying to
swim it's like no just try to Bob there
to keep this warm microclimate around
around you so if you get in cool water
and you don't move then you might start
shivering but for the most part that
doesn't happen so for women let's look
at a little bit warmer so we get the
same kind of responses and adaptations
that men have and if you do this in 55
degree water so it's more cool it's not
ice cold right what is the benefit to a
woman's
body by doing a cold plunge and how long
should you be in it so when we look at a
cold plunge the whole idea again is
environmental stress so we start to see
an improvement in our um parasympathetic
sympathetic drive so now we're able to
get into that calming um because again
body becoming resilient to stress we
have an increase in our body's capacity
for using glucose so we have better
insulin um sensitivity better blood
glucose control uh we have some signals
to lose some of that deep body fat and
we start to see better cardiovascular
responses but women do better in the
heat okay talk to me about this okay so
when we look at sauna exposure women can
tolerate heat a lot more than men so if
we get into a sauna that is 80 or 60
Celsius so that's on the upwards
of gosh metric math hold on I keep
forgetting you live in New Zealand I'm
like why are you talking Celsius I'm
like okay that's why and science sence
all that's true science science is
Celsius um 130 degrees okay we'll go
with that uh woman can sit in there sit
up high 20 minutes or so not sweating
yet right absorbing heat Vaso dilate
it's great so we're heating ourselves
our body's responding to it by uh what
we call heat shock protein responses so
these little proteins that will uncouple
and then recouple and and be better for
it so it's creating a whole cellular
change that then is like okay now we
have better responses within the muscle
the muscle can use uh glucose a lot
better it can use fat lot better we're
also uh increasing blood flow to the
brain we're also improving our blood
vessels so they respond to hot and or to
constriction dilation a lot faster which
is important as we get older and start
hit par menopause we start having blood
pressure problems and it also allows us
to hit higher temperatures on the
outside um so like summer times and
things without having an undue stress
because women by the nature of being
women struggle more in the heat so if we
environmental heat on the outside but
when you're in the sauna sitting there
it takes time for the body to heat up
because of our Thermo regulatory
differences between what men do when
they get in and they start sweating
profusely and then they get dehydrated
and they don't have time to adapt as
well to the heat as women do because we
baso dilate first and then we start
sweating so if you have access to a
sauna do you recommend that women sit in
a sauna for the health benefit yeah I do
how long like what what would you
recommend like if you have access to
this because I see a lot of the Bro
scientists out there talking about the
magical benefits of a sauna but now you
I'm I'm starting to go okay for dudes
but what about for me yeah and so what
is the benefit or the protocol for women
to get the maximum benefit for us so
when we're looking at for health
benefits and not performance benefits
because there's two different things so
for health benefits if we are doing 10
to 15 minutes twice a week bare minimum
you get health benefits and what are
they so this is better cardiovascular
health so better blood um flow better
blood pressure we have metabolic
responses so we have better blood
glucose control better fatty acid
metabolism so your body's like I'm going
to use more fat as a fuel like meaning
you're going to burn more fat if you sit
in a sauna you will use the circulating
fat as a fuel instead of storing it yeah
this is my kind of exercise by the way
that's great send this on and it
improves your exercise tolerance because
when you exercise you produce heat and
one of the living factors for women who
first start exercising is the
uncomfortableness of being hot oh and
then my my my face still turns like a
tomato bright red yes I just am there is
something about me that I I can lift one
weight and it's like Bing yep and that's
that Vaso dilation first that's how
women offload heat first and some women
say I don't ever sweat it's like well
because your body is offloading the heat
so much through vasod dilation and
you're not in a hot enough environment
to absorb more heat so your body can
Thermo regulate and be be fine even when
you turn bright red and you hate it
another question that a listener had is
should you eat before or after a workout
this depends on what you're doing so we
know first thing in the morning we've
already talked about it that you need to
eat before you go if you are exercising
in the afternoon and you had lunch maybe
2 hours before
then you don't necessarily have to eat
right before but you do have to eat
afterwards if you are doing what we call
metabolically taxing so high-intensity
exercise a cardiovascular session having
a little snack before and then having
real food afterwards is really
beneficial if you're just doing strength
training we see especially from the
research of Abby Smith Ryan at UNCC you
have around 15 grams of protein before
any kind of strength training session it
improves the post exercise Epoch or what
we say your metabolism stays elevated
after exercise for a longer period of
time and it improves your body's
responses to strength training so I
guess the short answer is ideally yes
you'd have some protein before but if
you're really pressed for time and it's
in the afternoon and if you had a meal
within 2 hours not
necessarily um you in your work talk
about supplements like creatine and
caffeine MH could you talk about why
women in particular need to pay
attention to these two creatine is
something that's always thought of in
the bodybuilding set where you see big
muscly guys and they're using creatine
because it's a it's a metabolite or it's
an essential thing in muscle contraction
which allows our our muscles to contract
really quickly and then recover and
contract quickly but what we also see is
it's beneficial for all the fast
energetics in our body so we think about
brain we think about gut heart all of
the things that use energy quickly
because it has to creatine is involved
women by the nature of being XX have
about 80 70 to 80% of the stores that
men do primarily because men have more
muscle but also women tend to eat less
so we don't have as much coming in and
our liver only makes about 2 to three
grams a day if we supplement with it
then we see everything improves our
brain health improves our gut health
improves cardiovascular problems start
to dissipate and we have better muscle
function so there's an incredible body
of research that's being done for
creatine for health for women we see
it's beneficial in pregnancy it's safe
to take in pregnancy and it's really
beneficial we see it's really important
for mood and cognitive function in women
who repair and postmenopausal and then
for skeletal muscle health and bone
health we see that it's beneficial just
a small dose so we're thinking 3 to 5
gram so that's a half a teaspoon that
you might put in your water or something
once a day doesn't have to worry about
timing takes about 3 weeks for it to
actually saturate the body so you know
you want to kind of be patient and after
that you're going like wow why have I
not been taking this it's so important
well now I'm like wow I need to be
taking this because it's so important
here we go um what is your advice for
women who are struggling to balance
nutrition M and a busy LIF
Style part of it is being prepared I
know it's hard when we talk about that
consistency and
preparation um but then part of it
reality right so it's like okay I know
from being on the road it's hard to eat
how I want to eat and I go to a
restaurant and there's a salad and
there's lots of stuff in it and I'm
going to be one of those people it's
high maintenance I'm like I don't want
dressing can you put some extra veggies
in there great so I have to make it work
for me if you are super busy and you're
like running out the door to get the
kids to school and then going straight
to work and you're coming home and
you're starving and you got to make
dinner and then you have to do all the
things that we all have to do we have to
be a little bit prepared so I'm not
saying take all of Sunday and prepare
the week's meals because that's just not
appropriate if we do our protein coffee
or overnight oats and we know what we're
going to have and then we might have
snacks in our bag I have snacks in my
car that don't perish like I have nuts I
have a couple of protein bars I have
some Tetra packs of almond milk I have
single sachet of protein powder just
things that I'm like shoot I forgot oh I
have it in the car or I have it in my
bag and it's just something that's not
ideal but it is things that my body
needs to get through and I always make
the Precedence to have as much fresh
fruit veg and whole grains at every meal
that I have so that I'm taking care of
my gut microbiome because if we take
care of a gut microbiome then it feeds
forward in so many positive ways for
mood and health and Immunity and I think
that's one of the things that's missing
from looking at I come from New Zealand
here and I go into a grocery store and
I'm like whoa there are rows and rows
and rows of of supposed food but nothing
to eat because of all the ultr processed
sugar stuff that's on there with all the
marketing so again we go back to the
grandparent idea shop the perimeter get
as many fresh fruits and veggies and
then you know there are some canned
things that you can get and some frozen
things you can get but really think what
am I eating that's going to protect my
gut if the person that's listening takes
just one thing from this conversation
which is going to be hard to do because
you taught us so much
today what would the one thing that you
want that person to walk away with and
focus on to
be it's hard to make change and I want
women to feel ownership of their own
body
and it starts with consistency and
making time for yourself it doesn't have
to be a lot of time it could be 10
minutes first thing when you get up and
you might do some Mobility you might do
stretches you might do every minute on
the minute of squats and push-ups for 5
minutes but something that is you and
you own it and it helps you become more
centered and you're consistent with that
it doesn't mean you have to get up and
make time to go to the gym it doesn't
mean you have to take time out of family
I mean if you go to the playground with
your kids in the afternoon move around
have fun make the kid playground the
adult playground right it's consistency
and what are you doing 10 minutes a day
just for yourself you know one of the
things that I'm excited about is that
you know there will be millions and
millions of people that listen to this
yes and if every person that listens
shares this with one or two women in
their life or young women in their
life the number of lives that will
change simply because of the things that
you've just flipped on our head about
the way that we think about strength
about why you need to exercise in terms
of intentional stress and stress
resilience protein coffee has just
changed my life doctor I mean just
everything I've I had it all
wrong and for a long time and because I
didn't know right and because I've been
listening to the advice by men for men
yeah and I am so grateful that you're
here and I'm grateful that you have
chosen to listen to this and that you're
going to share this with women in your
life because I think what you're asking
us to do feels like it's accessible and
it makes sense and I'm excited to try it
all and I'm just wondering if there was
a mantra that you would love every woman
to turn to another woman after they hear
this or turn to their daughter and say
or some something that like truth that
we need to be telling each other and
reminding each other that we've all
gotten wrong what do you want us to tell
the women in our
life oh well I could joke around and say
women are not small men because that's
easy to say but in all reality my big
focus and push is creating body
positivity right and the body positivity
is how we feel in ourselves and how we
allow our friends to talk and to feel
about themselves because we could have
all the body positivity that we want and
feel really fantastic but if we're
surrounded by friends who don't have
that same empowerment and same body
positivity it's heartbreaking so being
able to share that and say you know what
take up space I want to be empowered and
I want you The Listener to be empowered
to say I deserve that lifting platform
in the back of the gym and I'm going to
go there and if there's a bro there
who's looking at me funny I'm just is
going to take the barbell and say I own
this space because I want every woman to
know that they have a right in every
place in every gym every situation to be
strong empowered and feel positive about
the space that they're in so if we can
turn to each other and say it's about
being empowered and having body
positivity then that feeds forward to so
many different things it's a good role
model for our kids it allows us to have
more connection with our workmates our
Partners it improves empathy because as
an expat I look and I travel so much and
there is a huge lack of empathy
everywhere I land here in the states and
I feel it so if we can just share the
positivity and empowerment despite
what's going on in the world then that
just improves all the things that we
have in our lives and if every person
that hears this shares this with someone
else and everyone starts to move maybe
10 minutes a day I just think about the
positive effect it has on mental health
and the rolling forward that will have
on so many different things well Dr
Stacy Sims you just made a huge
difference in my life you have
completely shifted the Paradigm in terms
of how I think about exercise and what
it is and why it matters and you've also
explained why so many of the things that
I've been doing just don't work and why
and now that it makes sense I feel more
motivated yay to do exactly what you're
telling me to do and I am so excited to
also change the narrative in my family
with my daughters yay about getting
strong and becoming stress resilient and
actually operating in a way where we're
not acting
like little men yeah we're acting like
powerful women so thank you thank you
thank you thank you and I want to thank
you for truly taking the time to listen
to something that will change your life
and that is teaching you how to work
with the design of your body and that is
also empowering you to make a huge
difference in the young women and the
women in your life by sharing this and
in case someone else tells you I want to
tell you that I love you I love you for
the fact that you do want to do better I
love you for the fact that you love
science-based information I love you for
the fact that you're willing to say you
know what screw it I am going to go into
that gym and I am going to do something
uncomfortable because I deserve to feel
good in my body and that means I need to
start prioritizing doing it and now what
I really love for all of us is that Dr
Stacy Sims gave us a matter of fact
science back simple step-by-step guide
to exactly what to do to work with the
design of your body as a woman and now
all you need to do is go do it all
righty I will be waiting for you in the
very next episode I'm going to welcome
you in the moment you hit play I'll see
you there and for you you sitting here
watching with me on YouTube I just want
to say please share this with somebody
don't just sit and watch please do
something and take a minute and
subscribe to this channel because it's
really a way that you can support me in
bringing you new videos every single day
and I'm sure you're looking for
something really inspiring to watch to
really move you so I want you to check
out this video next