what would be the ideal breakfast for
anyone whether like and let's just talk
about the person who just wants to move
more they want to take better care of
their body they want to understand how
their body works so that you're getting
better results and you're feeling better
in your life so what would breakfast
look like just on an average morning if
you know for anybody yeah that I will
say that it's a hard one because people
have different food preferences how
about an avatar what's an avatar a a
makeup person okay a makeup person
makeup person so we'll say there's a
woman who is plant-based but not
vegetarian know so she has a preference
for plants three kids you know super
busy wakes up has been waking up tired
but wired didn't sleep well was like
okay I need to make this change never
hungry in the morning so we can split
her breakfast it could be overnight oats
which is chiaia seeds oatmeal some um
milk or or oat milk to soak it then when
she gets up she's like I'm going to
split that in half the first half I'm
going to add some berries and maybe
another tablespoon of Greek yogurt CU
then I'm going to get some protein
carbohydrate some Fiber and it's going
to calm me down it's going to tell my
brain yep ready to go okay then
you either are going out for your walk
maybe you're going to do some home
strength training maybe you're meeting a
friend for a session maybe you're taking
15 minutes of Just Breath work to to
bring yourself down especially if you're
the Avatar of three kids in a busy life
just taking that moment to put yourself
first and then when you get back maybe
it's an hour hour and a half later you
have the second half the second half of
those overnight oats with a few more
tablespoons of Greek yogurt and some
nuts and berries because then you're
getting the protein carbohydrate so
you've actually split your breakfast but
you've given your body the benefit of
food on different eating opportunities
without being over full but at the end
you end up with 30 grams of protein over
the course of a couple of hours so it's
easy you can mix it up do it the night
before you know that I'm not that hungry
but if I have a little bit and then over
the course of a couple of weeks you're
going to find that you're going to wake
up go yeah I need some food and this is
kind of a reset of your circadian rhythm
your body is starting to fall in line
your hypothalamus is understanding your
appetite hormones are starting to work
properly and when all of that feeds
forward then you're going to start to
see changes in body composition because
you're having better sleep because we
can't change anything if our sleep is
perturbed so the more we focus on how
are we going to work with our body's
natural rhythms and the way that our
hormones work the the more it feeds into
better parasympathetic drive for better
sleep I have just so screwed this up
like I literally wake up I delay the
coffee I exercise on an empty stomach I
then have my coffee which I'm then
drinking on an empty stomach which means
I've now maximized stressing myself out
and then I'm slamming something that has
30 45 grams of protein after I work out
and so what have you done if you are the
kind of person like I am that you've
bought into all the BS and you've
basically been starving yourself in the
morning and even if you get out for a
walk how are you kind of actually not
only not getting the benefit but you're
making it worse what's happening in like
the person's body when you do not feed
yourself first thing in the morning as a
woman yeah I always bring it down to
what are we doing when when we want to
exercise right we're looking for better
blood glucose control we're looking for
better bone we're looking for better
muscle if you're not eating then you are
not going to get better at any of that
stuff because the body again is like I
need fuel for the stress that's
occurring and I need fuel for the
exercise so if you've been brainwashed
like I am MH and you're exercising
because you are trying to like lose
weight or you're trying to look thin
MH what is happening if I continue to go
down that route where I don't eat before
I exercise and I'm basically starving
myself and I'm going for my walk and I'm
delaying food you lose muscle and then
the other thing when we look at women
who are late 30s early 40s onwards we
get a signal to put on more visceral fat
so that's that deep belly fat that that
metabolically active that can be
dangerous so I'll see women who are at
you know doing the same Pursuit and
really proud of the fact that they're
intermittent fasting they're not
breaking their fast till noon they've
had their coffee to hold them through
and you do a DEA and what's a DEA a DEA
is when you go and you get a complete
body scan so it looks at your muscle it
looks at fat where Fat's put it looks at
how dense your bones are so we see their
dexa results and on the outside they
look healthy right but on the inside
it's a bit of a scary story where we see
low bone density we see an increase of
fat accumulating in the belly area which
means that it's more what we call
metabolically active so you see a change
in your um cholesterol so you have more
of the quote bad cholesterol that's