the more glucose spikes you have the
faster you age wow and this shows on
your skin and your organs slowly age
today three out of five people are going
to die of an inflammation based disease
if you want a healthy body a healthy
mind you need to make sure you're not on
a glucose roller coaster your body
doesn't care whether sugar came from an
orange juice or whether sugar came from
a beetroot and is now in a can of
Coca-Cola those sugar molecules will
both lead to a glucose Spike
before we jump into this episode I'd
like to invite you to join this
community to hear more interviews that
will help you become happier healthier
and more healed all I want you to do is
click on the Subscribe button I love
your support it's incredible to see all
your comments and we're just getting
started I can't wait to go on this
journey with you thank you so much for
subscribing it means the world to me the
number one Health and Wellness podcast J
shett J shett the one the only J shett
what is glucose and why is it important
to understand it I love this question so
glucose is also called blood sugar right
and glucose is your body's favorite
source of energy so make a fist right
now with your hand okay so as you're
doing this the muscles in your hand are
burning glucose to contract and for
everybody listening to us right now the
cells in your brain are currently
burning glucose to understand what we're
saying right every single part of your
body is burning glucose every nanc to
keep you alive and as human beings the
main way that we provide this very
important glucose to our body is by
eating Foods specifically by eating two
categories of foods starches so that's
bread pasta rice potatoes oats and
sugars anything that tastes sweet from
an apple to my favorite triple layered
chocolate cake okay so we eat starches
and sugars and we give glucose to our
body so you might think okay I want lots
of energy who doesn't want energy so if
glucose is my body's energy I should
give my body as much glucose as possible
I should eat as many starches and sugar
as as possible well that's actually not
the case I love to take the image of a
plant do you have any plants at Home
many okay so you know that in order to
keep a plant alive you need to give the
plant some water but what happens if you
give the plant too much water it dies
exactly and the human body is similar
some glucose everything's going great
too much glucose and problems start
happening most of us are giving our
bodies too much glucose and this leads
to whole bunch of symptoms cravings for
sweet Foods chronic fatigue brain fog
inflammation faster aging hormonal
issues and then longterm the development
of type 2 diabetes so so my whole
purpose is to teach people how to eat
the foods that they love the starches
and the sugars in a way that's not going
to cause problems so how do you keep
eating the spaghetti and the cookies and
the bread in a way that is not going to
damage your health that's the whole
thing and that's what I really
appreciate about your work and why I'm
excited about this conversation because
I think a lot of us think oh no I have
to cut things out completely or oh no
I'm going to have to completely shift
everything and actually you're saying
there's maybe that is the case actually
let's go there yeah let's talk about
that is there a need what is it that
needs to be fully cut out are there
things that we need to definitely avoid
in those two buckets that you just
shaped for us well we really don't need
sugar we don't need to eat sweet Foods
at all it's really just for pleasure
your body doesn't need that amount of
glucose that amount of sugar so when we
eat sweet stuff whether it's fruit or
chocolate cake we're doing it because it
releases dopamine in our brain dopamine
is the pleasure hormone so sugars we
could do without but listen I want a
chocolate cake for my birthday I don't
want to eat broccoli for my birthday you
know and it's all around us sugar is
delicious it brings us this pleasure so
of course if you could completely cut it
out it would be better for your health
but I don't think that's realistic for
most people I don't have that kind of
willpower and I haven't seen you must
know people who have completely cut out
sugar but it's quite difficult what
about you what's your sugar consumption
like so I'm an extremist which means I
either I'm eating no sugar so when I was
a monk I didn't eat sugar for three
years but then I can easily drop back
into eating sugar every day because my
mother raised me as someone who ate a
chocolate bar a chocolate biscuit a
chocolate yogurt and a chocolate ice
cream every day growing up chocolate
brother yes I When you mention that
chocolate Triple A Cake and you post I'm
like that is my dream and I have had to
through my wife's coaching through your
work had to develop a healthier
relationship with sugar because I
believe a few years ago I was genuinely
addicted to sugar and I want to talk to
you about that and for me it's taken a
lot of retraining a lot of steps in
between where now I'm back being the
extremist where I'm not eating uh
refined sugars at the moment but at the
same time I would allow myself on my
birthday or an occasion to allow myself
to enjoy and indulge I've just I was
wearing a glucose
monitor for about 3 to six months like
last year and I was shocked I was
absolutely surprised at the types of
things that spiked my glucose levels I
would eat a nonsugar cereal as a test
and that would take it to bad
immediately not even average it was bad
immediately on the glucose levels talk
to us about glucose spikes and why are
people measuring their glucose level
what does that show us and what are we
trying to get our glucose to map so when
we eat a meal or food that contains a
lot of glucose so for example a
chocolate cake is a is a good option
good example or a plate of pasta or
anything else that starts you a sweet
when we deliver that glucose very
quickly to our body we experience what's
called a glucose Spike which means just
a rapid increase in how much glucose is
in your body and if you're wearing a
glucose monitor you will see this it
will look like this mountain that's just
rising and rising and rising and then it
crashes you don't need to wear at
glucose monitor to understand the
benefits of my work by the way but it's
a cool visual tool so what happens in
your body when we we Spike why is it bad
for us there are three main mechanisms
that are going on on a physiological
level that make these spikes damaging
the first one has to do with our
mitochondria the mitochondria are the
PowerHouse of the cell most people
remember that from biology class so your
mitochondria are these little factories
inside your cells that are responsible
for turning glucose molecules into
energy okay they're incredibly important
the problem is when you give them a
glucose Spike so when you deliver them a
bunch of glucose molecules very quickly
they break down they kind of go on
strike you know it's like when you have
so much to do on your to-do list that
you're just like I can't do anything I
have to go nap that's the feeling they
get they're like overwhelmed by all
these glucose molecules and they cannot
do their job properly anymore and so
what happens you feel this as fatigue so
you keep eating this sugar and these
carbs but you're exhausted you wake up
in the morning you're tired going to the
grocery store is exhausting playing with
your kids is draining your mitochondria
are not functioning properly anymore and
that's why one of the main symptoms of
having glucose spikes which most of us
have is this sense of chronic fatigue
now the second thing that happens in our
body when we Spike has to do with
cooking
so you know if you put something in the
oven like a chicken and it goes from
pink to Brown the chicken has cooked and
the Browning process is called glycation
the chicken has glycated it has cooked
now a human being from the moment we're
born we're slowly cooking we're slowly
glycating I know it sounds weird but
it's true for example if you look at the
cartilage of babies it's white but if
you look at the cartilage of somebody
who's 100 years old the cartilage is
brown we glycate we Brown as we age and
so much so that glycation is actually
pretty similar to aging and then when
we're fully glycated when we're fully
cooked when we're fully aged we die so
glycation is a process that we can't
stop We Can't Stop aging you know
there's billionaires trying to reverse
aging but so far they haven't been able
to but we can slow it down or speed it
up and glucose Spikes have something to
do with this right glucose and glycation
kind of sound like similar words it's
because it is the glucose that is doing
the glycating the Aging yep the cooking
the cooking so the more glucose spikes
you have the faster you age wow and this
shows on your skin wow you get more
wrinkles and your organs slowly age as
well so that's the second thing I had no
idea yep I did not know that yep wow mhm
mhm and the third thing that happens
when we have a glucose Spike well all of
these processes so the mitochondria and
the glycation they also increase
inflammation and inflammation is just a
nasty thing in the human body it causes
lots and lots of issues today three out
of five people are going to die of an
inflammation based disease so
inflammation is not good you want to
bring that down and the third thing that
happens when we have a glucose spike is
that your body knows that these spikes
are not good for you your body when it
senses this big glucose
it calls your pancreas and it's like hey
we need to get this glucose down so your
pancreas sends out a hormone called
insulin and insulin is amazing and she
grabs all the excess glucose molecules
and stashes them away into your liver
into your muscles and into your fat
cells and that's one of the ways that we
gain fat on our body but then too much
insulin over time that's the reason we
get type two diabetes so essentially you
have mitochondria fatigue glycation
inflammation diabetes IES and then a
whole bunch of other symptoms you might
feel depending on your personal health
history like brain fog like hormonal
issues that could lead to infertility
etc etc basically what I'm saying Jay is
that if you want a healthy body a
healthy mind you need to make sure
you're not on a glucose roller coaster
because otherwise it's going to be very
difficult for your body to function and
for you to feel your best if you're
experiencing glucose spikes on a daily
basis what are some of the Hidden
places glucose is that we may not see or
may not understand that we can't figure
out on a day-to-day basis because I feel
like when I went to that test of the no
sugar cereal in my head that didn't have
glucose only for me to understand it was
the rice that it was made from that was
having that impact on me so where is are
there any others that you know that are
hidden actually breakfast food is
usually a top offender right so orange
juice fruit smoothies breakfast cereal
even if they say no sugar or low in
sugar that doesn't mean they don't
contain glucose it just means they don't
contain any table sugar but they could
also contain sugar from fruit which is
quote unquote natural so it doesn't have
to be claimed as an added sugar in a
package right breakfast foods huge huge
huge offenders um and then kind of like
funny things that you wouldn't expect
like eating a lot of
grapes yeah if you eat 50 grapes that's
actually a lot of sugar because the
fruit that we eat today has been bred to
be extremely high in sugar and
concentrated in sugar but I think
breakfast foods are one of the biggest
ones oh also dried fruit people don't
realize that it's not because something
comes from fruit that it's good for you
dried fruit or fruit smoothie or fruit
juice can contain you know tens and tens
of grams of sugar even though it
originally came from a fruit but your
body doesn't care whether sugar came
from an orange juice and is now in an
orange juice or whether sugar came from
a beetroot and is now in a can of
Coca-Cola right those sugar m molecules
will both lead to a glucose Spike yeah
and it's interesting because I think the
way we've been trained to have a sweet
breakfast I've switched to savory
breakfast last year and that's something
you are a big big bigon yeah talk to us
about that switch well listen the
glucose Spike that we experience after
breakfast is going to control the rest
of our day so if you eat in the morning
something that is pure glucose like most
of us do right I grew up on orange juice
and Nutella crepes so I know sounds
amazing it was amazing but then at 10:30
I was exhausted because I was crashing
my glucose levels were crashing and I
was super super hungry because after a
big spike you experience a big crash and
that crash activates the craving Center
in your brain and literally tells you
Jay go find some chocolate you know and
you cannot resist what that voice sounds
like and you can't resist that urge so
your breakfast if you're having a big
glucose bike at breakfast you're setting
yourself up for a day of Cravings
fatigue inflammation and you're going to
feel quite awful an important switch to
make is to switch from a sweet breakfast
to a savory breakfast built around
protein right whatever kind of protein
you like maybe it's Dairy maybe it's
tofu maybe it's protein powder maybe
it's leftover fish from last night maybe
it's eggs whatever kind of protein you
want that's going to keep your glucose
levels nice and steady add some healthy
fats in there and you can have some
starch like a slice of bread for Taste
but importantly a Savory breakfast
contains nothing sweet it except if you
want some for Taste some whole fruit
right and you know all those sweet
breakfast foods that you love you don't
have to say goodbye to them completely
the best time to have them is for
dessert after lunch or after dinner
because if you eat something that
contains a lot of glucose something
starchy or sweet after a meal the
glucose molecules are not going to
arrive as quickly into your bloodstream
because that's already going to be food
in your stomach the worst time to eat
starches and sugars is breakfast because
your body is super empty so anything you
eat goes to your bloodstream in a second
right but it's actually the meal of the
day where most of us eat just starches
and sugars yeah think about the typical
breakfast orange juice oats with honey
on them breakfast cereal you know fruit
smoothies oatmeal with raisins exactly
and then you wonder why most of us feel
so terrible throughout the day why it's
400 p.m. and we're exhausted and we need
coffee or Red Bull we have cravings all
throughout the day and even at night
your breakfast controls how you feel for
the whole day and I think switching from
a sweet breakfast to a savory breakfast
is almost like you know in the movies
when they go through the mirror it's a
parallel universe yeah and you really
feel so different absolutely so so so
different all of a sudden you have
steady energy your brain is clear you
feel good you feel like yourself you're
not controlled you're not a victim to
these Cravings anymore yeah I found
though that as someone who has had
cravings for a long time or lived in
that sweet cycle there's been a lot of
withdrawal symptoms I think when people
stop eating sugar I've definitely
experienced headaches I think some
people experience very low energy
someone was telling me earlier today
that they feel nauseous or or sick like
there's a lot of different things that
come with it talk to us about why it's
so addictive yeah obviously beyond the
fact that we love the taste of it why is
it so addictive and how does it cause
those symptoms I think what you're
talking about is if somebody goes cold
turkey and just completely Cuts things
out and that's not actually something
that I recommend I think that again like
I don't have that kind of willpower um
and I want to help people improve their
health without having to give up the
sugar so even if you delay the sugar
from breakfast to after lunch as dessert
you're not going to get all those
withdrawal symptoms you're still going
to be able to enjoy it and get the
dopamine but with less impact in your
glucose levels and listen sugar is
addictive right and that
dopamine is very very very very
addictive and as human beings eating
something sweet is a very easy way to
get a hit now what you're talking about
can also be due to if somebody
completely cuts out carbs so starches
and sugars completely let's say from
today to tomorrow you cut out all carbs
that can cause issues because if you've
been eating carbs your whole life your
body expects these carbs every two to
three to four hours and your body is
actually just burning glucose for energy
so all of a sudden you cut off its
supply of glucose and it becomes a
little bit stressed out especially if
your body's not used to also burning fat
for fuel in a healthy body you can
switch from burning glucose for energy
to burning fat for energy easily so
either you eat glucose and your body
gets energy that way or you're not
eating and your body's burning fat in
most of us we're eating every two to
three to four hours some carbs and so
our body doesn't know how to burn fat
for fuel anymore it doesn't have that
muscle so so the idea is to train it
slowly to be able to do that not to just
cut out completely the glucose you know
cut the grass from under the foot too
quickly that's going to be difficult
yeah and I think that's one of the
biggest challenges right because when it
comes to New Year resolutions or when it
comes to changing habits we often think
we have to go in or out I hate that and
diets you know they don't work they're
super stressful they're actually a
pretty strong way to control women like
I have been from from the moment I was a
teenager the magazines are telling you
lose five pounds in a day you know lose
your belly before summer you're
bombarded by these messages that make
you feel inadequate if you're not on a
diet I mean it's pretty messed up the
amount of fat on your body or how much
you weigh is not a good representation
of the internal health of your body
right absolutely and if you're just
focusing on I want to lose weight I want
to lose weight there are very unhealthy
ways to do that that might actually make
your health way worse what I like to
teach people is these simple hacks so
save breakfast is very important one
eating sugar as dessert instead of on an
empty stomach is another key one and
these hacks are going to help your body
on the long term and create Better
Health from within and you might lose
weight for example in my experiment
about half the people lost some fat on
their body without trying to without
counting calories without cutting out
Foods just because naturally that's
where their body wanted to be and it
readjusted right but the objective is
not weight loss the objective is being
craving free and not feeling victim to
finding sugar three times a day or not
victim to the pot of ice cream at the
back of your freezer after dinner good
energy so you can actually live the life
you want to live and go after your
dreams you know that's the point and
play with your kids and have time for
yourself and then improving any medical
condition you might have from mental
health to infertility to diabetes weight
loss consequence but it's not the whole
point it's not a diet you know yeah and
it's a different shift in mindset really
because you're saying that a lot of us
are addicted to weight loss weight gain
or or something like that and you're
actually saying well let's make it about
energy let's make it about Focus let's
make it about make health health yeah
yeah which is which is which we just
haven't been trained to think that way
you know we haven't even I grew up
always feeling like oh if I didn't put
on weight then I must be healthy and
that's such a I mean it's such a
rudimentary belief around what health
and well-being is absolutely and it's
shifting you know we're now
understanding that's not the way to go
we need to focus on health not body size
or absolutely body weight absolutely
what should someone eat at 300 p.m. when
they're tired because everyone has that
post lunch you know
slump slump they they do but it actually
can go away if you study your glucose
levels and if you no longer have these
spikes you don't have to feel that
postmeal slump anymore because generally
that slump comes from your glucose
having spiked and now dropping because
after every Spike there's a drop and
this drop can make you feel really
really really tired so if you feel those
symptoms of the postmeal crash the best
thing to do is to start with your
breakfast so have a savory breakfast
then the second thing I would recommend
is at that at lunchtime make sure that
you start your meals with a specific
type of ingredient that is going to help
balance your glucose levels and before I
tell you what that is I want to tell you
about this amazing research study Jay so
researchers looked at a meal and they
found that if participants ate the
elements of that meal in a specific
order they could reduce the glucose
Spike of the meal by up to
75% huge that's huge without changing
how much they're eating without changing
what they're eating overall just by
changing the order and when I was in
school I remember uh biology teachers
telling us oh when you eat it all
becomes a big soup in your stomach
and so I thought how is this possible
how can the order in which you eat the
elements of meal have an impact so the
research is fantastic it turns out that
when you start your meals with
vegetables the fiber in the veggies when
you eat it first has time to coat your
upper intestine and create a sort of
protective mesh okay like a shield on
the walls of your intestine and that
Shield then slows down how quickly the
the rest of the meal is going to access
your bloodstream how quickly the
molecules from the rest of the meal are
going to make their way into your
bloodstream and so veggies first is this
very important hack now the scientist
always my veggies L really because you
hated them yeah because you're right you
eat all the Cobbs First and all the rest
of it like oh yeah and you know actually
so when you go to restaurants they often
give you bread at the beginning of the
meal yeah and actually it's pretty smart
so I think there's a whole conspiracy
here because if you give people some
bread at the beginning of your meal so
you're super hungry you eat the bread
bread is starch it turns to glucose so
very quickly you experience this glucose
Spike and about 90 minutes later you're
crashing and that's when the waiter
comes over and is like hi anybody would
like some dessert and at that point
you're feeling this intense craving for
sugar because of that glucose drop so
you're going to order dessert wow that
that makes sense to me I love bread at
the St and end but the best thing to do
actually is to delay that bread and
first have your veggies and then have
your main dish and have the bread you
know during the main dish or after the
main dish and that way you can still
enjoy the bread but the glucose
molecules are going to be protected by
that fiber mesh and not going to create
that big of a spike so you won't feel
those Cravings 90 minutes later you
won't feel the energy crash so that's
another super important hack and if you
do nothing else just at your next meal
eat what you would normally eat just add
a plate of vegetables to the beginning
of your meal and it can be three baby
carrots it can be some beautiful roed
cauliflower with tahini or whatever it
can be some salad it can be any sort of
veggies you have in your fridge and
tomatoes count as well and you'll see
how different you feel after the meal no
crash no cravings and you know you're
also helping your body become healthier
from within and interestingly Jay this
hack actually has a lot of parallels in
cultural habits so you know I'm French
and in France we have this tradition of
crud at the beginning of a meal which is
raw veggies MH in Italy they have
antipasti which is generally vegetables
at the beginning of the meal in the
Middle East you usually start your meals
with herbs eaten by the bunch MH so none
of the stuff I'm talking about is that
revolutionary it's kind of common sense
but we've lost touch with these
traditions and now we understand the
science behind them so I want us to
bring them back yeah that's spectacular
there was a study you were about to
quote and then I cut you off tell me
with my I don't know you were about to
say and the study says and then I said I
used to eat my vegetables L I don't know
what that was I think I was just talking
about the food order so 75% and so
ideally from a scientific standpoint you
would always start your meals with the
veggies then the proteins and the fats
and then the carbs last the starches and
sugars last now you know that's a
scientific theory and if you want to
decompose your meal and do that specific
order you can but I think from this
science we can just extract the most
important piece of information which is
veggies first and the carbs towards the
end of the meal to reduce the spike I
think that's so practical I think all of
us can at least do that with whatever's
on our plates and if we can just make
that shift today we're going to start to
see the benefit and that will hopefully
push us in that direction exactly and
then naturally you crave less sugar and
you feel better and it's these small
tweaks and you don't have to cut out
Foods we're not talking about
restricting how much you're eating I'm
actually telling you to add food to your
meal and that is going to improve your
health so veggies first that's another
very key hack that I recommend people
try out how off is the recommended daily
amount of grams of sugar on any given
packages right so if you look at any
processed food or any packaged food it
will say this is 30% of your daily
amount how wrong is the daily amount
well so the American Heart Association
recommends no more than 25 gram of added
sugar I think for women and 50 grams for
men something like that but we don't
need any of this sugar we don't need to
eat any sweet stuff at all your body
does not need sugar to live so that is
an upper limit if you will yeah that's
an upper limit we're seeing it as the
basic requirement it's like saying uh I
don't know three cigarettes are allowed
a day it's like it doesn't mean you
should smoke cigarettes it means like
that's the upper limit after which real
problems start happening but it's better
to have
zero but then what these recommendations
don't take into account is when are you
eating the sugar is it first thing in
the morning so you're increasing
inflammation brain fog increasing risk
of diabetes hurting your mitochondria
having cravings aging faster or is it
after a lunch that had fiber at the
beginning of a meal where the impact is
going to be way less hardcore in your
health so if you if you just keep eating
the same amount of sugar as you're
eating but you just change when you're
eating it that's the first step you're
already going to see a big impact on
your health MH and then Second Step
could be reducing amounts for sure and
naturally because you're not creating
that cycle of
addiction you're going to have fewer
cravings for the sugar anyway there's
this other really cool study I want to
tell you about so scientists put
participants in an fmri scanner you know
those big donut scanners okay so they
were looking at their brain activity and
as the participants were in the scanner
there was a screen in front of their
eyes and the screen showed images of
food chocolate cake Donuts broccoli
Burger Etc and the scientist asked the
participants to rate how much they
wanted to eat that food from 1 to 10
okay like one is like I don't care 10 is
like I want to eat this right now and
the participants were hooked up to a
machine that was measuring their glucose
levels in real time and this is what the
scientists found they found that when
people's glucose levels were steady they
were rating all the foods like fiveish
Burger fiveish broccoli fiveish so you
know no particular Cravings but then
when the participants glucose levels
were dropping two things happened first
thing on the brain scan the craving
Center was activating and second thing
they started rating all of the sweet
Foods really highly okay and that just
goes to show that you cannot control
these Cravings they come from a deep
part of your brain that goes on to alert
mode when your glucose levels are
crashing because it is a dangerous thing
for the body right your body doesn't
know that that crash came from a spite
cuz you just ate 15
Donuts your body thinks it's low on
energy yeah um and so all this to say
that as you study your glucose levels
this craving Center will activate less
and less so naturally you're not going
to want to eat as much sugar and you're
going to switch from a situation in
which you were controlled by those
Cravings to a situation in which you'll
eat the sugar you really like for
pleasure for enjoyment without feeling
controlled M so instead of feeling like
oh my God I need to eat something sweet
right now give me anything any chocolate
bar it's more like hm you know what
tomorrow I want to go to my favorite
Bakery and get my favorite pastry you
know from a sense of like agency tot and
strength and boundaries versus being a
victim to that sugar addiction yeah you
can you can have that delayed
gratification exactly exactly no that's
huge I mean two things that really
helped me with this and I notice when
I'm weaker and this obviously happens
with the amount of travel I do and I
totally notice how that impacts my
desire for more sugar and I found that
one of the biggest commitments I had to
make was eating my meals on time every
day and that started to reduce craving
so when I was having breakfast at a
certain time lunch at a certain time and
dinner at a certain time I found myself
having less cravings and filling the
gaps with less sugar when I was missing
breakfast so I was missing lunch and
then I was trying to make up for it then
i' would be willing to take anything as
you're saying and the second thing I
found was when I had poor sleep when I
was sleeping badly or I wasn't sleeping
enough I would wake up craving sugar to
want to get me to the next meal and then
naturally I'm going to have all these
things that aren't great for me because
I just haven't slept well and I found
that those two things had a massive
impact but how is what you're saying
having a an impact on the other way so
I'm saying how these lifestyle choices
impact my glucose Cravings but how are
our glucose levels impacting our well
for example sleep so sleep and glucose
are go hand in hand and so what you're
describing is if you wake up and you
haven't slept well you have more
cravings and you know what else happens
which is kind of unfortunate is that
when your body is tired it cannot
regulate your glucose levels as well so
anything you eat will create a bigger
glucose Spike right so for example if
you have that cake on a day when you're
rested versus a day when you're super
exhausted the exhausted day the cake
will make a bigger Spike you're eating
the same take but it's creating a bigger
Spike therefore a bigger crash therefore
more cravings and so when we're tired we
tend to crave more sweet foods and that
that makes a bigger Spike and a bigger
drop and then in turn being on a glucose
roller coaster also makes your sleep
that night worse not as deep not as
restorative so you start this vicious
cycle okay here's what to do to break
the cycle first of all use the hacks
when you wake up right so if you're
tired have a Savory breakfast
second thing to sort of reset your
glucose balance is to exercise even just
5 minutes so next time you wake up and
you're tired do five minutes of jumping
jacks put on a YouTube video five
minutes you know exercise anything
that's going to get your muscles working
is going to help you manage your glucose
levels better that day and then as you
study your glucose levels you will
notice you will sleep better and often
people will tell me that they used to
wake up in the middle of the night with
a pounding heart you know sweats that
can be because your glucose levels are
crashing as you're sleeping wow yeah and
that's why in my study so many people
improve their sleep not by taking
sleeping pills not by changing what's
happening in their bedroom just by
changing how they're eating everything
is connected Jay you cannot just look at
one thing in isolation when you improve
your glucose levels so many systems in
your body improve it's remarkable so you
might be entering this because you want
less inflammation or few cravings but
then what happens is you realize oh my
skin is better oh I sleep better oh my
mood has improved you know all these
amazing side effects it's really
beautiful to watch Yeah you mentioned
mood there what's the connection between
blood sugar levels and mental health
because I think again even though we are
making those connections now I think
often we don't recognize how correlated
our diet and our mental health is that's
the reason I got into this in the first
place so when I was a teenager I had an
accident I broke my back jumping off a
waterfall had very intense surgery I
have lotss of metal in my back now and
physically I was fine because you
recover fast when you're that young but
then my mental health started going
really down the drain so anxiety
depression
depersonalization my I felt like my
brain was completely broken I didn't
feel like myself anymore and I went on a
journey to try to understand how to get
better and that's what got me studying
biochemistry that's what got me into
genetics and then almost 10 years after
my accident 10 years of Darkness I
finally had my first clue I was part of
a pilot experiment and during it I could
wear a glucose monitor and I saw Jay
that the days where my glucose levels
were spiking and dropping a lot my
mental health was worse and the days
where my glucose levels were steady my
mental health was so much better and
this changed everything for me because I
had been completely lost for the better
part of a decade trying to understand
what the heck I could do to improve my
mental health and I was lost let me tell
you and nobody said oh you should look
at your lifestyle but in that moment I
remember that day I was feeling one of
these episodes come on of
depersonalization which is this horrible
mix of brain fog feeling like a stranger
in your own body I mean it's terrible
and I scan my glucose monitor and I see
one of the biggest glucose spikes I had
ever seen and so I started putting two
and two together I said wait a minute is
it possible that this glucose spike is
actually causing this episode anyway so
that opened the gates really wide for me
I was like wow this is fascinating and I
started doing all the research I could
and I I saw that I wasn't alone that
most people experience glucose spikes on
a daily basis even if they don't have
diabetes and that these spikes are
correlated to all the things we spoke
about and to Mental Health M so as I
started managing my glucose levels my
mental health started improving and so
what's the connection well the cells in
your brain also use glucose for energy
and so you know those three things I
talked about the mitochondrial damage
the glycation the inflammation the
insulin your brain cells also feel these
consequences of spikes and we don't
fully understand how the brain works but
we do understand that when these things
happen in the brain it's not
good we also know that glucose spikes
impact tyrosine levels and tyrosine is
an important molecule that regulates our
mood I want to talk you about another
really fun study can I okay yeah please
fascinating so bless these scientists
they're so amazing okay so let me tell
you what this study is so scientists
recruited 200 married couples MH they
gave each person in the couple a voodoo
doll representing their spouse wow I
know they told the married people to
please over the next six weeks put a pin
in the voodoo doll every time your
spouse annoys
you and then at the end of the six weeks
the scientist got all the voodo dolls
back with all the pins in them and they
measured the participants glucose levels
they found that the people who had the
most irregular glucose levels had put
the most pins in the voodoo doll
representing their spouse and that's
where the tyus
hypothesis started com coming up they
saw that being on a glucose Roc cooster
can impact how irritable you are how you
see those around you how nice you are
how triggered you are by your spouse so
if you ever feel irritated agitated like
oh it's so annoying this person hate
them well maybe your glucose levels have
something to do with it so whether
you're trying to improve irritability
hungriness mental health anxiety
depression whatever managing your
glucose level again is a key foundation
in the house of your health yeah and for
me like it wasn't everything right after
I managed my glucose levels I had to go
to therapy do EMDR do lots of other
stuff but it gave me a foundation that
was so necessary as that first step yeah
well I think what you're laying up there
for us and that's definitely what I've
discovered in my own journey of mental
health and well-being is just that
you're just making it harder for
yourself when you're not using
everything at your disposal and I was
definitely someone who had used
mindfulness and meditation in order to
master the mind but I didn't realize how
hard that was when your body was slowing
you down and actually if your body was
with you the kind of Revelations and
breakthroughs you could have were
Limitless but when your body wasn't with
you or for some people when their mind's
not with their body it slows you down
and it makes everything so much harder
and I couldn't recommend that more to
people like if you're someone who loves
meditating and you love mindfulness but
you're not taking care of your body and
you're not looking your glucose levels
or your sleep take a look at it it's
only going to make you a better
meditator and if you're the other way
around where you're like Jay this you
know the physical stuff for me is easy I
feel really fit and healthy it's really
important to add the other side as well
because you have no idea how good you
can feel it's all connected and to give
you another example um I've been
recently really into weightlifting so it
feels really good my body feels strong
and I've noticed also my mental
resilience has improved as my physical
resilience has improved so I'm able to
manage stress better I feel stronger and
that's because you train your nervous
system your body and your brain are
connected by your nervous system right
and so when you improve your physical
health your nervous system improves and
your mental health improves as well it's
all it's all connected absolutely is
there a more ideal food before or after
workouts oh great question so this
actually brings me to another hack which
is the hack about movement so as your
muscles contract and as you exercise or
even as your you're just you know
walking your muscles are burning glucose
for energy and we can use this
information to our advantage so the hack
I recommend is after eating one of your
meals a day after one of your meals a
day use your muscles for 10 minutes go
for a walk play with your dog tidy your
apartment I'm a very messy person so I
do that one a lot tidy your apartment do
some calf raises if you're at your desk
at work why not go to the gym you know
go weightlift because as you do this
your muscles are going to be using some
of the glucose from the meal you just
ate M and if you're an athlete and
you're doing some very intense exercise
your body is going to use up most of the
glucose from whatever you eat so the
more you exercise the more you can eat
glucose before or even after actually um
and you experience much less of a spike
so if you want to eat a cookie or
chocolate cake before after workout is
actually a pretty good time to do it
that way a lot of the glucose will go to
your muscles instead of causing a that's
what I've been trying to do so the
reason I'm asking is for myself one of
the things I struggle with is usually
I'll wake up I'll meditate in the
morning and then I'll drink a tea or
something like that like a a warm herbal
tea and then I'll go on a hike or I'll
go and work out because I've never
really found what to eat before my
workout that's great for me and then
when I come back I'll eat breakfast I'll
have my Savory breakfast and I feel good
and everything feels fine but I often
wonder could I be doing something better
before I go out on my hike which which
can be like it'll be 30 minutes normal
and then 30 minutes intense incline if
you do eat something before going
working out maybe a banana or something
do you feel like you're able to work out
better do you feel like you have more
energy more explosivity that's a great
question I think I'd have to monitor
that to give you an like a honest answer
and I would say that in the past I've
tested things like dates but then I was
worried that that was going to SP that's
very high in sugar exactly so I had that
recommendation from someone I tested it
out I was like when I learned about
everything to do with glucose I was like
wait a minute that's probably not a good
idea how intensely are you exercising
are you just walking no so that's what I
mean it's it's it's probably 30 minutes
like easy and then 30 minutes of like
explosive incline but it's not it's not
high intensity in that it's not all fast
it's self-paced but it is all uphill for
30 minutes for example if I don't eat
before I work out I don't perform as
well right because as you're eating
something that contains glucose that's
going to feed your muscles very easy
easily accessible energy so you could do
some tests I I don't think dates are
necessary because they're very high and
sugar but you could even try something
like you know a piece of sourdough bread
right with an avocado on it or a a
banana with some Nut Butter you don't
have to have something so sweet and
concentrated as a date but do some tests
see what works for you now I know some
options yeah you could even I like the
avocado and S that's sounds you could do
some almonds um you could do yogurt with
some
berries try some stuff out and see
because you might find that you're
actually walking faster yeah yeah yeah
that would be good for me yeah
definitely sometimes about going up that
hill going why am I doing this today and
and and I completely agree with and
would you say it's the same for weight
training before weight training is that
the same typ of f big time Big Time
especially if you're doing something
like weight training which is you know
more explosive than walking or running
you have to really your muscle need to
be able to go P you know so yes
absolutely so my nutritionist put me on
to this a couple of years ago and I
hated it but then when I saw you like it
was one of your big pillars oh I know
what you're about to say you know what
I'm about to say yeah go on vinegar yes
yeah so I was drinking a cup of vinegar
like the little whatever the shot of
vinegar why a shot of vinegar before
tell us first of all a shot is not good
you should always dilute it because if
it's a shot it's going to hurt your
teeth I was literally doing a shot so
I've got to change that you got to
change that it's a lot easier to dilute
yeah okay so vinegar contains a
wonderful molecule called acetic acid
and acetic acid when you have some
before a meal is going to slow down how
quickly food breaks down into glucose in
your body so it's kind of like slowing
down digestion and this is really really
good it makes you feel Fuller full
longer and the glucose molecules arrive
more slowly into your blood and that's
the whole point so the heck is before a
meal that's going to be high in carbs
have one tablespoon of vinegar in a big
glass of water I was not doing that 5 to
10 minutes yeah well no wonder you
didn't like it if you had to do a shot
like gosh and it can be any type of
vinegar apple cider vinegar white wine
vinegar Cherry vinegar whatever you just
want to avoid the very syrupy like
balsamic glaze that one's no bueno
because that's full of sugar this is an
easy hack and again science has shown us
that this ingredient that most of us
have in our kitchen actually has a
wonderful effect on our health and it's
been used for m Millenia I mean vinegar
has been around forever but now we
understand the science behind it it's a
great hack and what all what before
every meal or just lunch or is there a
depends on how you feel I recommend
before the meal of your day that's
highest in sugar or starch right um and
one of thing you can do is you know how
I was explaining veggies first is so
important you don't have to drink the
vinegar you can also make it into
dressing oh I like the and put it on
your veggies okay that's you're making
it easy now so you know the salad with
some vinegret dressing
wonderful way to start your meals
wonderful you get the fiber from the
veggies making that mesh and you get the
vinegar slowing down breakdown of food
you're golden got it okay now I can get
back on it cuz I've been avoiding it it
was so hard I was like I have to ask you
about it today I'm not surprised I was
doing a shot of vinegar and and you're
right about the teeth as well I'm so
sorry that's terrible that's kind of
gross iame it was really hard to have
and yeah every time I'd have it it would
almost feel like it could start some
reflux or it could have like uh you know
that's not great oh I'm sorry no no it's
good but as you can see this is another
really easy hack it it's free it doesn't
ask you to add any to remove anything
you're just adding stuff and helping
your body at the same time and then I
like to see these hacks as sort of an
on-ramp to freeway you know you kind of
you kind of get on them and then after a
few days you feel so much better and
everything becomes easier in your life
yeah no that's great what about for our
snackers our snackers that are listening
who are saying Jesse I love this advice
I can do that for my but I'm a big
snacker and I turn towards I mean today
if you look at it whether it's a protein
bar but I guess protein bars is such a
common go-to snack but they have really
high sugar it depends on the bar yeah it
really depends so look at the
ingredients always and if you so when
you look at the ingredients list on the
back of a product they are ordered by
weight so if the first ingredient says
sugar that means sugar is the most
important ingredient in that product and
then they decrease right in in in weight
so if you see in the first five
ingredients of anything whether it's a
protein bar or yogurt if there's any
type of sugar in the first five
ingredients then that product is
dessert okay so if it says like that's
such a great tip and it doesn't have to
say just sugar it can say something like
date puree honey dextrose fruit juice
concentrate it has in glucose Revolution
I have the whole list but manufacturers
use lots of fancy words words to not
make it sound like just cane sugar but
actually it's just cane sugar it's all
the same molecules right so sometimes
you could your body's not telling the
difference as you said no difference so
that's for the protein bars and then for
the snackers okay I have a hack that's
called putting clothing on your
carbs anytime you eat carbs so carbs
being starches or sugars make sure to
never eat them naked and by naked I mean
on their own mhm so never snack on just
a piece of bread or never snack on just
a cookie always add some clothing which
means protein fat or Fiber which means
for example adding some avocado to the
bread or some cheese which means for
example adding five almonds to the
cookie or a Greek yogurt right so if you
love snacking remember this hack put
clothing on your carbs never eat your
carbs naked that way you'll have less of
a glucose bike because the risk Jay is
that our snacks kick off that Cravings
roller coaster because between meals our
stomach is empty so same concept as for
breakfast you don't want to eat too much
sweet stuff otherwise it's going to make
a big spike and you're not going to feel
very good 90 minutes later this is
actually Genius Like if you're listening
to this right now none of us have any
excuses to shift this around genuinely
I'm listening to you just going thank
you like thank you so much because I
think it's so often when you're hearing
about how to change your diet and your
food it just sounds so hard and so
complex and it feels like like God where
do I even start with this and and here
we are just making really basic
connections that that we can all do very
very simply and it helps you with your
energy with your mood with your skin but
also for serious health conditions like
type 2 diabetes this is the way out
right if you have type two diabetes if
one of your parents Grandparents has it
it can be quite challenging to know how
to get out of it and it can feel like
either I have to go on this extreme diet
and never eat carbs ever again or I'll
do this medication and what I want to
offer with these hacks is an easy way to
take back some control over your glucose
levels because type two diabetes is
reversible it is not a genetic
hereditary disease that you can't do
anything about you can improve it I see
people put it into remission every
single week using this work in concert
with their doctor of course but this is
the kind of stuff that can turn your
health around and instead of getting
sicker as you age your health can
improve as you age and don't we all want
that that's the dream you know
absolutely
yeah absolutely in the book you about
there's some research that says that
eating fruit first in the without any
other Foods is best for digestion would
eating it as a singular food first thing
in the morning impact blood sugar like
what's your take on that well you know
this this idea of oh if you eat fruit as
dessert it's going to rotten your
stomach or it's going to purify that's
kind of a urban myth that's been
floating around so if you look at the
ideal food order from that science you
should eat the sugar last right and
fruit is also in the sugar category and
so how do you reconcile both of those
things and people have asked me a lot
about this concept of oh fruit for
dessert is going to rot in your stomach
turns out there's no scientific evidence
to support that nothing can rot in your
stomach nothing can purify in your
stomach sug sugar eaten last or fruit
eaten last does not do that okay now
even though most of us think that a
piece of fruit is super natural they're
like oh a banana or Peach like that's
Nature's Bounty turns out Jay the fruit
that we find today in supermarkets is
actually not
natural humans are very good at breeding
stuff so humans have bred gry wolves
into
Chihuahuas right and loads of other
breeds of dogs we've also bred our fruit
and our plants to be very sweet and full
of sugar if you compare a banana from
today to an ancestral banana
they look nothing alike the ancestral
banana is small full of seeds full of
fiber quite tart modern day banana is
basically dessert same for apples apples
used to be small like cherries now
they're this big nice little plump
package of water and sugar
essentially if you want to eat something
sweet the piece of whole fruit is still
the best thing to eat because of that
protective fiber and I explained the
fiber makes that mesh in your intestine
but then as soon as you denature a piece
of fruit whether you juice it you take
away the fiber you blend it you
pulverize the fiber then it becomes just
one big glucose bike waiting to happen
and it's not because something comes
from fruit that it's good for you yeah
that's a really good explanation I
appreciate that I think there's always
been people who've demonized fruit as
well in that way but I think that
explanation actually gets into the
nuance and subtlety of how we're having
our fruit and I never going to say Don't
eat fruit it's totally fine to eat fruit
seriously it's much better to eat fruit
than a cookie right for your glucose
levels for your body and it is still an
unprocessed food right it's been bred
and Chang that's the but it's still
unprocessed so of course have fruit just
don't denature that fruit totally
because then you're taking it even
further and further away from the way
nature intended us to consume it yeah I
actually remember when I first went to
India with my mom and my mom was making
me the same cures that she would make me
in London but now making them when we
were living in India just for a bit we
went visiting when I was younger and
it's so interesting because each
vegetable was so flavorful but so
different and I'm sure you feel this
back home or when you're traveling like
you can find these places in the world
where you're eating real vegetables
again or real fruits and they don't look
as perfect they all look imperfect
random yeah they've got personalities
and even the flavors are not consistent
so like a zuun is going to taste
different to another one but it's still
so flavorful but in such a unique way
and and I remember saying to my mom like
what are you doing here like what are
you doing differently in India that
you're not doing back in London it was
just what was accessible and and I think
that's in the states for sure where I
feel that even more than from London
where in London I still felt certain
vegetables and everything were still
accessible but here I I really feel like
a lot of the vegetables and fruits that
we're eating are super processed y yeah
yeah absolutely it's really tough uh one
of your other hacks uh is stop counting
calories and I wanted to talk about that
because I think that's what all of us do
and again that again the recommended
2,000 for women and 2500 for men seems
to be like such a big figure that we
focus our whole diet plans on and lives
on I love this question do you know Jay
how people used to measure the amount of
calories in a food I don't know okay so
if they wanted to measure the amount of
calories in a donut here's what they
used to do they would put the donut in a
little box box and they would put this
box in a bigger like an aquarium like a
big Basin of water okay they put the
doughnut box at the bottom of the
aquarium and then they would light the
doughnut Inside the Box on fire the
doughnut would burn and then they would
measure by how many degrees the water in
the aquarium increased oh my gosh so and
that would give you the number of
calories in the donuts the calories is
just a measure of how much heat
is given up when something is burned so
if you were to put an avocado in that
box and burn it it might increase the
water temperature around it by the exact
same number of degrees therefore you
would say this doughnut and this avocado
have the same number of
calories now it seems pretty obvious
that this is kind of a silly way to
measure food it's almost like saying oh
this book and this book have the same
number of pages Pages therefore they're
the same book yeah this is not the case
right my book and your book might have
the same number of pages but they're not
about the same topic they're not from
the same author they don't give you the
same information don't give you the same
emotion right and so if we just talk
about Foods based on how many calories
they contain we're missing what's
actually key what is in that food what
are the molecules in that food is that
food just glucose and going to create a
big glucose bike or is that food just
healthy fats and protein and going to
keep your glucose level steady to give
you another example two people could be
eating the exact same number of calories
let's say two women are eating 2,000
calories a day one of them could be
eating in a way that keeps her glucose
level steady feel great energy
functioning mitochondria clear brain
going after her dreams girl boss
whatever the other person could be
eating 2,000 calories in a way that's
creating lots of glucose spikes
inflammation aging type two diabetes
hormonal issues brain fog etc etc etc
how many calories you're eating does not
tell you how healthy you are does not
predict your health at all you need to
learn about what you're eating and in my
book I explain how to identify the
molecules in a food and if you follow my
hacks and you stop counting calories
naturally your health is going to
improve you might be eating the exact
same number of calories as before but
your life will be completely different
calories are not enough information
they're interesting to measure the
quantity of a food for example one dut
versus two Donuts but they're not
sufficient and it's really easy to hide
behind calories when you're for example
a food manufacturer and you're making
processed foods and you say there's only
50 calories in this little bag of sweets
don't worry it's not bad for you it's
just 50 calories yeah but it's 50
calories of pure sugar and it's going to
make you feel horrible so calories are
not enough we need to evolve past this I
want to teach people what is in their
food I want to make every single one of
my readers a food detective I want them
to have all the agency the power the
information to make informed choices
when they go to the supermarket that's
the goal right giving people that
freedom and that power that's what I
care about yeah that's such a brilliant
Mission like that's such a brilliant
Mission because even everything you've
said to us today whether it's being able
to know what to look at on the back of a
pack all the way to putting clothing on
your cars I just I was just about to say
that like putting clothing on your like
I love that it comes for you in your
heart and mind from a place of giving
people agency and giving people strength
and rather than making us fearful which
I think a lot of diet plans do a lot of
food advice does it makes us quite
insecure and scared that we're doing the
wrong thing whereas when I'm talking to
you I feel a sense of like enthusiasm
and confidence I know what to do good
and that's so that's so fulfilling like
it's so it fills you with so much
enthusiasm and energy
to to feel like yes I am in control of
how I'm going to feel and what I'm going
to eat you are and the information is
there and I'm I just want to apologize
to all the people who've been
manipulated by food marketing diet
culture that stuff stop it can stop if
you get this information this will stop
and the thing that breaks my heart the
most Jay and I think this is what
motivates me to do this work is when I
meet somebody who has a medical
condition like type two diabetes and
everybody wants to make the right
choices every everybody wants to be
healthier but because of the
manipulation and all the misleading
information about food they're eating in
a way that they think and they hope is
good for them but is actually making
them sicker and that's what I want to
stop I want to insert this information
in this science in those situation and
turn it all around for people yeah I
love that I love that uh Jesse we talked
about so many things today but one thing
I wanted to ask you about was the use of
supplements I take a lot of supplements
every day I felt better because of them
it's had a big imp impact on my personal
life and I was always someone who was
playing around I think supplements are
also things that you have to test and
experiment and see what works for you as
a combination what's your take on
supplements well I know supplements in
the glucose space right and I can't
comment on all the other stuff I'm sure
there's great things for other stuff
you're trying to optimize but when it
comes to glucose so people often ask me
instead of doing the vinegar hack can I
take a vinegar gummy when I can't have a
veggie starter can I take fiber pills my
dad has diabetes doesn't want to change
his diet what can I give him and I spent
the last few years researching
extensively this space and what are some
cool molecules that could actually help
your glucose levels unfortunately what's
on the market today at worst actually
contains sugar and creates a glucose
bike under the guise of going to help
you with your glucose levels and that's
just so annoying to me and there's some
good stuff out there but I've actually
created something incredible that is the
best thing on the market if you want to
help your journey to steady glucose with
a supplement now I'll explain what it is
but I don't want people to think this is
a magic pill you should do the food
hacks first and foremost okay that is
going to have the biggest most powerful
impact on your health but a supplement
can also help so I've identified four
plants Jay that have existed forever but
that recent science has shown have an
incredible impact on our glucose levels
these are white mulbury leaf lemon
extract cinnamon and antioxidants from
green vegetables I've put them all
together into a capsule you take it
before a meal and it reduces the glucose
Spike of your meal by up to 40% wow and
this is more powerful than vinegar which
was up to 30% I know me I got some for
you good I'm being serious I've got some
so if you want extra help this is the
thing you need it's called anti-spike
formula you can find it on my website
antis spike.com and it not only has this
immediate impact on the glucose Spike of
a meal it also builds up benefit over
time it reduces inflammation it reduces
your fasting glucose levels it increases
gp1 which is a hormone we've spoken a
lot about recently in the media because
of things like OIC gp1 is a really cool
hormone that just makes you feel Fuller
and OIC tricks your brain into thinking
there's more gp1 in your body than there
actually is but with anti-spike you're
actually harnessing natural Pathways to
increase it for real mhm so this is my
latest creation and I hope it's going to
help a lot of people you know when
you're 4M birthday party when you're
traveling when you can't do the hacks
anti- Spike will be there for you but
again do the food hacks first it's just
an additional hack to help yeah yeah I
want to try it for sure I have it in my
yeah I love that what is your take on
asmic I mean based on what you just
mentioned there what's been your
assessment of it I'm sure you've seen
people who are on it yeah listen I think
for a lot of people it's been kind of a
godsend um they've really struggled
their whole life with their weight and
for some people that's their objective
right so whether you take it or you
don't take it it's not my place to judge
but what I found Jay is that if you
think about it this craze has shown us
that we live in a society in which our
food system is so toxic that we need to
take a pill to prevent us from eating
the food around us do you understand how
sad that is so I just feel a bit worried
and a bit disheartened we've gone to
we've gone to that place and also when
people lose weight on OIC they don't
just lose fat they also lose muscle mass
and so when you stop taking oing and if
you um gain weight back you often just
gain fat back and so overall you're in a
worse place so whether or not you take
it it's important to learn my hacks so
that way when you stop it you sustain it
right but um yeah I mean wow wow what
can I say crazy world we live in yeah
absolutely and I appreciate you touching
on that cultural challenge that we have
on a number of parts in our conversation
and I really think that that's at the
heart of a lot of what you're saying is
that everyone out there who's listening
right now who feels
like they don't like the way they eat
they don't like what they eat they judge
their body they look at the mirror first
thing in the morning and criticize
themselves it all comes from programming
and conditioning it's not your fault
it's not your fault and it was you were
set up to feel that way yes and there's
a lot of money being made off your back
because you feel that way yeah and so I
think a lot of people we beat ourselves
up we think oh what's wrong with me or
there must be something really bad with
me or oh my gosh I'm not disciplined
enough and I don't have good it's not
about discipline it's not about Laz
everything Temptation choices yeah toxic
food around you that's cheap mising
marketing messages you know incorrect
information so we need to go back to
teaching people how their body actually
functions in the science and the
physiology and you know Jay I hope I
will become completely irrelevant I hope
this information will be so common
knowledge people will be like yep wear a
sunscreen drink water brush your teeth
have a savory breakfast like I want my
stuff to be at that level and I want to
retire and disappear because everybody
needs to know this it should be taught
in schools it's basic right to
understand how your body functions and
how to navigate this difficult food
landscape that we live in absolutely and
and the courage that any of you have
right now who are listening and even
wanting to take one step towards that
agency that Jesse's been talking about
that's a huge win because we're
operating in a society where even taking
that one step is often so difficult
because of all the messages we're
hearing around us so anyone who's
listening and about to take that first
step uh go and order a copy of glucose
Revolution right now uh the
life-changing power of balancing your
blood sugar and of course check out
antis spike.com uh to figure out if you
need to add that once you've done uh
Jesse's hacks and Jesse we end every
conversation with a final five which is
our Fast Five on the podcast and I'm
excited to see what you answer so they
have to be answered in one word to one
sentence maximum got it so Jesse here
are your final five the first question
is what is the best advice you've ever
heard or received when it comes to
health symptoms are
messages I'm going to let you expand
because I like that okay yeah if you
feel symptoms from acne to psoriasis to
infertility to brain fog these are not
something to suppress they are messages
they are your body trying to communicate
with you to tell you hey there's
something wrong I need your help don't
suppress don't feel bad about the
symptoms flip the script talk to your
body be like okay why is there all this
eczema on my arm what's going on that's
inflammation that's inside can I help
you you see what I mean so symptoms are
messages how how do you think we often
process symptoms instead of as messages
we think our body is fighting us we're
like body why are you against me we
don't understand it's crying for help
it's not against your body just wants to
keep you alive your body's not trying to
be annoying I promise your body's trying
to keep you alive that's so good that's
so good I love that your body is not
trying to be annoying I love that no
it's so true your body is so much
smarter than you so much smarter than
you listen to it it's got stuff to teach
you that's such great Insight next time
you come we're going to talk about that
I love that that's really hit Accord
with me like I think it's so interesting
how we look at anything inconvenient
as there's something wrong and and and
you're being annoying and I wish you
would just be okay rather than oh wait a
minute you're actually trying to share
something and I think a lot of people at
least I've heard I don't have kids but
I've learned that a lot of people feel
this with their children where your
child's trying to communicate with you
and just doesn't know how and it's
almost like our body's like that yeah
it's like a baby doesn't cry because
it's trying to annoy you a baby cries is
going through something difficult and he
wants your help yeah I love that that's
such a beautiful answer all right second
question what is the wor best health
advice you've ever heard or received um
have a fruit smoothie first thing in the
morning yeah I mean anything that has to
do with uh fruit juices fruit smoothies
as being a health food anything no just
like no yeah don't do it do it don't do
it okay uh question number three what's
the first thing you do in the morning
and the last thing you do before you go
to bed the first thing I do in the
morning I take my earplugs out and I
drink water so you do have water first
in the morning that's it yeah absolutely
and then I try to turn my phone on a
little bit later I try to not turn it on
in the first half an hour last thing I
do at night before going to bed I have
this app in which I track my mental
health so I put a little a scale of one
to five how my mental health was today
and I write a couple sentences about my
day nice what is the app code it's
called Dao okay have no affiliation
whatsoever it's awesome d a y l i o and
I've been doing this for four years now
and it makes a little dot for I'll show
you in a sec it makes a little dot for
every day and so I have four years of
dots of how mental health was in all of
those days and I see these patterns I
see that I've gotten happier over time
more fulfilled have less episodes of
difficult mental health issues so it's
really cool to look back that's
beautiful I love that that's a great
recommendation for everyone listening uh
fourth question what's something that
you used to believe to be true about
health but now you've realized it's
actually not true uh that everybody
should wear a glucose monitor so when I
first started in the space because
wearing the glucose monitor had changed
my life I was telling everybody to wear
one and now I realize that you can get
all the benefits by seeing what I've
discovered and the science that I've
found and sometimes overt tracking
yourself can lead to issues and stress
yeah I I can relate to that there was a
point where I was measuring everything
yeah and it was useful and then it went
too far and then I didn't want to
measure anything and then it's it's a
it's a really interesting balance
because data can be so powerful and at
the same it can be so disempowering
because sometimes you look at the data
decide how you feel about yourself yeah
yeah it's like you know yeah you let
exactly you wake up and you're like I
don't know if I'm tired or not look at
my sleep data oh I'm exhausted clearly
because I didn't sleep all but you're
actually not connected to how you feel
yeah yeah and it takes you outside of
your body exactly exactly it's what
you're saying earlier we need to
actually get better at living in our
bodies and listening within our bodies
and hearing and feeling what they're
saying to us and how they're
communicating rather than expecting that
even even an external person or system
is going to somehow predict how we feel
amen yeah that's a really really
powerful take away I love that uh Fifth
and final question which we asked to
every guest who's ever been on the show
if you could create one law that
everyone in the world had to follow what
would it be okay I'm going to restrict
myself to the world of food okay because
there's lots of other laws that we could
do that would be very important in the
world and it can be a real law like you
know yeah yeah ban all processed
breakfast food m I love that love
because that would help kids it would
help parents it would change
people's mood make them happier more
fulfilled yeah I think that's a big one
that's huge or like the law could be
treat breakfast like any other meal
because if you ban something then other
stuff pops up so it's more like treat
breakfast as the second lunch and eat
lunch food at breakfast yeah that's
great I love that everyone Jesse in chop
the book is called glucose Revolution
the life-changing power of balancing
your sugar if you don't follow @ glucose
goddess on Instagram make sure you go do
that right away please grab a copy of
this book we went through the hacks but
we were just skimming the surface there
is amazing Insight amazing hacks amazing
steps and habit building processes
inside the book that are going to be
huge for you so I can't recommend this
book enough I would actually say that if
there's one book you read in 2024 I want
it to be this book so please please
please go pick this book up I think it
will change your life uh I don't think
I've ever emphatically mentioned a book
that way before on the show but I mean
it and uh I I can't thank you enough
Jesse for the work that you're doing in
the world and how much it's impacted my
personal life and how I feel and how I
think it's going to impact millions and
billions worldwide so thank you so much
thank you Jay I'm very grateful to be
here thank you and I hope you'll come
back soon with pleasure thank you if you
love this episode you'll enjoy my
interview with Dr Daniel aan on how to
change your life by changing your brain
if we want to Healthy Mind it actually
starts with a healthy brain you know
I've had the blessing or the curse to
scan over a thousand convicted felons
and over a hundred murderers and their
brains are very damaged