immediately not even average it was bad
immediately on the glucose levels talk
to us about glucose spikes and why are
people measuring their glucose level
what does that show us and what are we
trying to get our glucose to map so when
we eat a meal or food that contains a
lot of glucose so for example a
chocolate cake is a is a good option
good example or a plate of pasta or
anything else that starts you a sweet
when we deliver that glucose very
quickly to our body we experience what's
called a glucose Spike which means just
a rapid increase in how much glucose is
in your body and if you're wearing a
glucose monitor you will see this it
will look like this mountain that's just
rising and rising and rising and then it
crashes you don't need to wear at
glucose monitor to understand the
benefits of my work by the way but it's
a cool visual tool so what happens in
your body when we we Spike why is it bad
for us there are three main mechanisms
that are going on on a physiological
level that make these spikes damaging
the first one has to do with our
mitochondria the mitochondria are the
PowerHouse of the cell most people
remember that from biology class so your
mitochondria are these little factories
inside your cells that are responsible
for turning glucose molecules into
energy okay they're incredibly important
the problem is when you give them a
glucose Spike so when you deliver them a
bunch of glucose molecules very quickly
they break down they kind of go on
strike you know it's like when you have
so much to do on your to-do list that
you're just like I can't do anything I
have to go nap that's the feeling they
get they're like overwhelmed by all
these glucose molecules and they cannot
do their job properly anymore and so
what happens you feel this as fatigue so
you keep eating this sugar and these
carbs but you're exhausted you wake up
in the morning you're tired going to the
grocery store is exhausting playing with
your kids is draining your mitochondria
are not functioning properly anymore and
that's why one of the main symptoms of
having glucose spikes which most of us
have is this sense of chronic fatigue
now the second thing that happens in our
body when we Spike has to do with
cooking
so you know if you put something in the
oven like a chicken and it goes from
pink to Brown the chicken has cooked and
the Browning process is called glycation
the chicken has glycated it has cooked
now a human being from the moment we're
born we're slowly cooking we're slowly
glycating I know it sounds weird but
it's true for example if you look at the
cartilage of babies it's white but if
you look at the cartilage of somebody
who's 100 years old the cartilage is
brown we glycate we Brown as we age and
so much so that glycation is actually
pretty similar to aging and then when
we're fully glycated when we're fully
cooked when we're fully aged we die so
glycation is a process that we can't
stop We Can't Stop aging you know
there's billionaires trying to reverse
aging but so far they haven't been able
to but we can slow it down or speed it
up and glucose Spikes have something to
do with this right glucose and glycation
kind of sound like similar words it's
because it is the glucose that is doing
the glycating the Aging yep the cooking
the cooking so the more glucose spikes
you have the faster you age wow and this
shows on your skin wow you get more
wrinkles and your organs slowly age as
well so that's the second thing I had no
idea yep I did not know that yep wow mhm
mhm and the third thing that happens
when we have a glucose Spike well all of
these processes so the mitochondria and
the glycation they also increase
inflammation and inflammation is just a
nasty thing in the human body it causes
lots and lots of issues today three out
of five people are going to die of an
inflammation based disease so
inflammation is not good you want to
bring that down and the third thing that
happens when we have a glucose spike is
that your body knows that these spikes
are not good for you your body when it
senses this big glucose
it calls your pancreas and it's like hey
we need to get this glucose down so your
pancreas sends out a hormone called
insulin and insulin is amazing and she
grabs all the excess glucose molecules
and stashes them away into your liver
into your muscles and into your fat
cells and that's one of the ways that we
gain fat on our body but then too much
insulin over time that's the reason we
get type two diabetes so essentially you
have mitochondria fatigue glycation
inflammation diabetes IES and then a
whole bunch of other symptoms you might
feel depending on your personal health
history like brain fog like hormonal
issues that could lead to infertility
etc etc basically what I'm saying Jay is
that if you want a healthy body a
healthy mind you need to make sure
you're not on a glucose roller coaster
because otherwise it's going to be very
difficult for your body to function and
for you to feel your best if you're
experiencing glucose spikes on a daily
basis what are some of the Hidden