OK so moving on to more 8.04 things. Back to
atoms. So let's look at specifics of that.
I'm not kidding, they really are related to
black holes. I get paid for this. So here's
a nice fact, so let's get to atomic spectra.
So to study atomic spectra, here's the experiment
I want to run. The experiment I want to run
starts out with some sort of power plant.
And out of the power plant come two wires.
And I'm going to run these wires across a
spark gap, you know, a piece of metal here,
a piece of metal here, and put them inside
a container, which has some gas. Like H2 or
neon or whatever you want. But some simple
gas inside here.
So we've got an electric potential established
across it. Again, we don't want so much potential
that it sparks, but we do want to excite the
H2. So we can even make it spark, it doesn't
really matter too much. The important thing
is that we're going to excite the hydrogen,
and in exciting the hydrogen the excited hydrogen
is going to send out light. And then I'm going
to take this light-- we take the light, and
I'm gonna shine this on a prism, something
I was taught to do by Newton. And-- metaphorically
speaking-- and look at the image of this light
having passed through the prism.
And what you find is you find a very distinct
set of patterns. You do not get a continuous
band. In fact what you get-- I'm going to
have a hard time drawing this so let me draw
down here. I'm now going to draw the intensity
of the light incident on the screen on this
piece of paper-- people really used to use
pieces of paper for this, which is kind of
awesome-- as a function of the wavelength,
and I'll measure it in angstroms.
And what you discover is-- here's around 1,000
angstroms-- you get a bunch of lines. Get
these spikes. And they start to spread out,
and then there aren't so many. And then at
around 3,000, you get another set. And then
at around 10,000, you get another set.
This is around 10,000.
And here's the interesting thing about these.
So the discovery of these lines-- these are
named after a guy named Lyman, these are--
these are named after a guy named-- Ballmer.
Thank you. Steve Ballmer. And these are passion,
like passion fruit. So. Everyone needs a mnemonic,
OK. And so these people identified these lines
and explained various things about them.
But here's an interesting fact. If you replace
this nuclear power plant with a coal plant,
it makes no difference. If you replace this
prism by a different prism, it makes no difference
to where the lines are. If you change this
mechanism of exciting the hydrogen, it makes
no difference. As long as it's hydrogen--
as long as it's hydrogen in here you get the
same lines, mainly with different intensities
depending upon how exactly you do the experiment.
But you get the same position of the lines.
And that's a really striking thing.
Now if you use a different chemical, a different
gas in here, like neon, you get a very different
set of lines. And a very different effective
color now when you eyeball this thing. So
Ballmer, incidentally-- and I think this is
actually why he got blamed for that particular
series, although I don't know the history--
Ballmer noticed by being-- depending on which
biography you read-- very clever or very obsessed
that these guys, this particular set, could
be-- they're wavelengths. If you wrote their
wavelengths and labeled them by an integer
n, where n ran from 3 to any positive integer
above 3, could be written as 36. So this is
pure numerology. 36, 46 angstroms times the
function n squared over n squared minus 4,
where N is equal to 3, 4, dot dot dot-- an
integer.
And it turns out if you just plug in these
integers, you get a pretty good approximation
to this series of lines. This is a hallowed
tradition, a phenomenological fit to some
data. Where did it come from? It came from
his creative or obsessed mind. So this was
Ballmer. And this is specifically for hydrogen
gas, H2.
So Rydberg and Ritz, R and R, said, well actually
we can do one better. Now that they realized
that this is true, they looked at the whole
sequence. And they found a really neat little
expression, which is that 1 over the wavelength
is equal to a single constant parameter. Not
just for all these, but for all of them. One
single numerical coefficient times 1 over
m squared minus 1 over n squared-- n is an
integer greater than zero and greater in particular
than m. And if you plug in any value of n
and any value of m, for sufficiently reasonable--
I mean, if you put in 10 million integers
you're not going to see it because it's way
out there, but if you put in or-- rather,
in here-- if you put any value of n and m,
you will get one of these lines. So again,
why? You know, as it's said, who ordered that.
So this is experimental result three that
we're going to have to deal with. When you
look at atoms and you look at the specter
of light coming off of them, their spectra
are discrete. But they're not just stupidly
discrete, they're discrete with real structure.
Something that begs for an explanation. This
is obviously more than numerology, because
it explains with one tunable coefficient a
tremendous number of spectral lines. And there's
a difference-- and crucially, these both work
specifically for hydrogen. For different atoms
you need a totally different formula.
But again, there's always some formula that
nails those spectral lines. Why? Questions?