Moving right along, all
those subcortical bits, we're
just going to talk about three
of the most important ones,
the thalamus, this
big guy right smack
in the middle of the brain,
very large structure,
the hippocampus,
and the amygdala.
OK, let's talk
about the thalamus.
Think about the thalamus
as a Grand Central
Station of the brain, OK,
with all of these connections
going to all those
parts of cortex
coming in and out of
the thalamus like that.
OK?
So one of the key things
about the thalamus
is that most of the
incoming sensory information
goes by way of the thalamus
en route to the cortex.
OK?
So if you start with
your ear, there's
sensory endings in
your ear that we'll
talk about later in the term.
And they send neurons into
this, the thalamus here,
this yellow thing, through
a bunch of different stages.
They make a stop
in the thalamus.
And then they come up
here to this green patch,
which is auditory cortex.
OK?
Similarly,
somatosensory endings,
touch sensors in
your skin that enable
you to feel when
you're being touched
come in through the skin.
And they make a stop
in the thalamus.
And then they go up to
somatosensory cortex up there.
OK?
Similarly, visual signals
that come in from your eyes
make a stop in the thalamus and
then go up to visual cortex.
OK, what's the name of the
structure in the thalamus
that those axons
make a synapse in?
Coming up from the eyes,
you make a synapse here.
And you go up to visual cortex.
AUDIENCE: LGN.
NANCY KANWISHER: LGN, perfect.
What does it stand for?
AUDIENCE: Lateral
geniculate nucleus.
NANCY KANWISHER: Perfect.
OK, you should know that.
This is review from 900, 901.
OK, yes?
Sorry.
OK, which sensory modality does
not go through the thalamus
en route to cortex
between the sensory nerve
endings and the cortex?
Sorry?
AUDIENCE: Olfactory.
NANCY KANWISHER: Yes.
Yes.
You guys are on the ball.
Yes, olfactory system is
the one sensory modality
that doesn't make a
stop in the cortex.
You can sort of see that here.
From the nose, it goes straight
up into olfactory cortex
right there.
All right, so that's
the standard view
of the thalamus is this
kind of like relay station
where all the external sensory
information comes in there,
makes a stop, and then
goes up to cortex.
OK?
That's my thalamus act.
Boom.
Like that, right?
OK.
But, increasingly,
there's evidence
that the thalamus is much
more than a relay station.
And why would you bother
with a relay anyway?
Kind of doesn't mean anything.
Kind of means like
we don't know what's
going on here because
you wouldn't just make
a synapse for no reason, right?
OK, and so the
first thing to note,
is there are lots
of connections that
go back down the other way?
There are 10 times
as many connections
that go from primary
visual cortex
right here in me, right
here in this guy in red,
there are 10 times as many
that go backwards down
to the thalamus as go forwards.
That's mind blowing, right?
Information comes from the
eyes up into the brain.
What the hell are those things
doing going backwards, OK?
Well, they're doing all
kinds of interesting things.
So that's the first indication
that the thalamus isn't just
relaying stuff in a
stupid, passive way.
And the second
whole line of work,
which many people
are working on,
but I think some of the most
awesome work on this topic
is done by our own Mike
Halassa in this department.
And he does these
incredible studies
that you can do in mice with
these spectacular methods
that we can't use in humans,
where he can really take apart
the circuit and
magnificent detail.
And he's showing
that the thalamus
is involved in all kinds
of high-level cognitive
computations in mice.
It's really stunning work.
When the mice have to switch
from doing one task to another,
the thalamus plays a key role in
gating the flow of information
from one cortical
region to another, OK?
All right, moving along,
the hippocampus, I you
guys all learned about this.
The number one gripe
in this department
as we learn about
H.M. in every course.
So that's going to happen here.
But it's going to
last about 20 seconds.
So here goes.
That's a normal slice
of the brain like this.
Here's the hippocampus
on either side.
It's like a whole curled up deal
right there and right there.
And here is H.M.'s brain,
the famous H.M., who
had surgery to remove his
hippocampus on both sides,
and completely lost his episodic
memory for anything that
happened after his surgery.
OK?
You all remember that, right?
If anybody hasn't heard
of H.M., send me an email.
And I'll give you some
background reading.
OK, so very loosely,
the hippocampus
involved both in this kind
of long-term episodic memory
that H.M. lost.
And it also plays a
key role in navigation,
which we'll talk about in
great detail in a few weeks.
And I just want to say
that some cases are
even more extreme than H.M.
So there's a case of
Lonni Sue Johnson.
And I am trying to
get you guys a video.
And I didn't get it in time.
But I'll show it to you later in
the term if you're interested.
Lonni Sue Johnson
had a viral infection
that went up into her brain.
She was an extremely
accomplished person.
She did illustrations on
the cover of The New Yorker.
She was a pilot.
She had her own
farm in which she
raised lots of stuff, a
very smart, interesting,
multitalented woman, who
had this terrible tragedy
of getting viral
encephalitis at I
don't know what
age, but middle age.